<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and lively representation of popery shewing that popery is only new-modell'd paganism, and perfectly destructive of the great ends and purposes of God in the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Owen, Thankfull, 1620-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12439118</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12439118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53750)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 394:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and lively representation of popery shewing that popery is only new-modell'd paganism, and perfectly destructive of the great ends and purposes of God in the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Owen, Thankfull, 1620-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>82, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Everingham for W. Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Thankfull Owen. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:62067:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>March 12. 1678/9.</date>
               <signed>Guil. Jane, R. P. D. Henr. Epiſc. Lond. a Sac. Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and lively REPRESENTATION OF POPERY: SHEWING That Popery is only New-modell'd PAGANISM, AND Perfectly deſtructive of the great Ends and Purpoſes of God in the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 10.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Learn not the way of the Heathen —</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Stand faſt therefore in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and be not intangled again with the yoke of bondage.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Everingham</hi> for <hi>W. Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhops Head in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62067:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62067:2"/>
            <head>A true and lively Repreſentation of Popery.</head>
            <p>THAT there is but one true way to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is readily acknowledged by all that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this way lye on the right hand or on the left, whether through the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or in the Reformed Religion, that is made a Queſtion. And though the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> with confidence enough, vainly arrogate this to themſelves, as if there were no way to Heaven but by aſſociating and joining in Communion with their Church, and will hardly (unleſs in a good mood) allow a dying Proteſtant to be ſaved; yet I doubt not but I have ſufficiently made it appear, by ſuch evident and clear Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, as are within the ſphere and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an ordinary Capacity, not only that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion is hugely agreeable and ſubſervient to thoſe Grand purpoſes of God in the Goſpel for the Salvation of Mankind, but that Popery is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely prejudicial and deſtructive of them. And although (conſidering the various Artifices and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Stratagems the Popiſh Emiſſaries make uſe of, not only in gaining, but confirming their new Proſelytes) I cannot hope to recover ſuch as are already enſnared by them; yet I may reaſonably ſuppoſe that theſe few ſheets, if they chance to fall into the hands of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62067:3"/>ſome one or other who deſires impartially to ſeek and embrace the Truth where-ever he meets with it, or by what hand ſoever it be brought to him, may be ſo fully perſwaded and ſatisfied of the Goodneſs of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the groſs Impiety and Wickedneſs of the Popiſh, as that whatever cenſure he paſs upon this, yet of the other he may ſay, that <hi>God is in it of a truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I conſider therefore that the great End and Deſign of the Chriſtian Religion is to form in men the ſacred life and nature of God; for ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, That thoſe glorious and ineſtimable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which God through Chriſt was pleaſed to make to the World, were deſigned to recover men from their Sins and Corruptions into a participation of the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> And that we may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and think this to be a mere airy Notion and an inſignificant ſound of Words, our bleſſed Saviour himſelf expreſſes it by the name of <hi>The new Birth;</hi>
               <hi>Except a man be born again</hi> — And his Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtyles it the <hi>New Creature:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.</note> All which being of a like ſignification and reſpect denote a certain ſtate and condition of life,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15.</note> to which men are brought by the Power and Grace of God in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, whereby their hearts and minds are tuned into an univerſal Conſent to Gods holy will. That ſtate of ſin and miſery into which all men by their firſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication and Rebellion are involved, is nothing of the true nature of our Souls, but an Extraneous and Adventitious thing, a meer Uſurpation upon the Lords Inheritance, whereby the minds and ſpirits of Mankind are preternaturally forced againſt their proper bent and inclination; and God by the Goſpel
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62067:3"/>comes to free them from this heavy Preſſure and Bondage, and quickens and invigorates their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Powers, with a ſtrong and potent endeavour towards a Reſtitution and Freedom. And this <hi>Cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> or Effort whereby they endeavour to throw off their uneaſie load, is expreſſed and decypher'd in the Holy Scriptures by the Name of <hi>Spirit,</hi> as in
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. where the Apoſtle puts an oppoſition between the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> and ſays they are two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Laws and States of Being, the one tending whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the abaſing, and diſhonouring, and captivating the Soul to vile and low purpoſes, and making it drudge like a Slave to promote an Animal and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual life; but the other being nothing but a Law of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, and conſequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural to it, endeavours the freeing it from all that violence and force uſed upon it. And this very ſame active and enlivening Principle ſhall be ſo far quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and invigorated by the aſſiſtance of God's Holy Spirit, that it ſhall at laſt through his benign and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Influence break into a Flame, and conſume all Terreſtrial Dregs and Incumbrances, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talize theſe our dull and ſluggiſh Bodies. So the Divine Apoſtle tells us, <hi>If the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead dwell in you;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>he that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead ſhall alſo quicken your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bodies by the Spirit that dwelleth in you.</hi> Now that this bleſſed frame and temper of mind may be raiſed and renewed in us, God ſent his Son into the World; and he incites and encourages us to the attaining of ſo deſirable a State by mighty and ſtupendious Promiſes, ſuited and adapted to our beſt and higheſt Capacities: and that we may not think the participation of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62067:4"/>Divine Nature, or the new Creature, that is, that conſtitution of mind and ſoul which the Goſpel came to implant in us, to be a thing which we can have no rational Idea or Conception of; I ſhall give ſuch a brief and comprehenſive Character of it, as that Eternal Wiſdom has legibly engraven in the frame and contexture of the Chriſtian Religion. Thus therefore I conceive of it; That it is a Holy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Life and Power implanted in the Soul by the Spirit of God, bringing every Thought, Word and Action into conformity and obedience to the Divine Will, and begetting ſuch a natural and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſenſe of what is Holy and Righteous, that it is as hard for a man truly poſſeſſed of this excellent nature to act contrary to it, as to ſuffer a Diſciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his bodily life; and though we bear this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, and it be ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the frailties and infirmities of fleſh and blood, yet does it fill our minds with comfortable hopes and aſſurance that our mighty Saviour and Redeemer, who expreſſed the greatneſs of his love by dying for us, will perfectly releaſe and ſet it free from the heavy preſſure of thoſe Earthly Bodies, and at laſt Crown it with ſuch a body of Light and Glory, as he himſelf is poſſeſſed of in the higheſt Heavens, This is indeed the main end and ſcope of the appearing of the Grace of God to the World; and that the Son of God might take poſſeſſion of his own Inheritance, and effectually and fully accompliſh the recovery of Mankind from the cruel Bondage of Sin and Satan into this ſo deſirable a ſtate of Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, wherein their ſouls act with the greateſt eaſe and pleaſure, and conſtancy, and delight, he deſigned by the promulgation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62067:4"/>
            <p n="2">2. In the firſt place, the utter Extirpation and rooting Idolatry out of the World. For this is a ſin ſo heynous, and ſo derogatory to the Perfections of the Divine Nature, that however it may be ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and refined by the crafty Patrons of it, yet it doth moſt certainly thwart and croſs that glorious purpoſe of God in making men like to himſelf: And the reaſon of it is, becauſe it ſinks mens minds too much into Body and Matter, and ſo inſtead of purging their Souls from the groſs affections and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the Fleſh, it depreſſes and debaſes their thoughts to the loweſt degree of Senſuality. Now that when the Evangelical Diſpenſation ſhould take place upon Earth, all Idolatry was to be extirpated and deſtroyed, the Prophets of old have clearly te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.17, 18, 20. — <hi>The Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day, and the Idols he ſhall utterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: In that day a man ſhall caſt his Idols of Silver, and his Idols of Gold, which they made each one for himſelf to worſhip, to the Moles, and to the Bats.</hi> That this Prophecy reſpects the times of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, is acknowledged by the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, and may receive a further confirmation from the ſecond and third Verſes: <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days, that the Mountain of the Lords Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills, and all Nations ſhall flow unto it — For out of</hi> Zion <hi>ſhall go forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>i. e.</hi> That in the days of the Goſpel (which is frequently denoted in Scripture by the <hi>laſt times</hi>) the worſhip of the true God ſhall take place, and be eſtabliſhed among all Nations; and that this Evangelical Diſpenſation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62067:5"/>which ſhould be carried and propagated over all the world, ſhould begin from
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of our Lord Jeſus received their full and compleat Inauguration into this Office of preaching the Goſpel, by the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt upon them; and then in that day all the falſe Gods and Images of the Heathens ſhall be utterly thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitle, and men ſhall honour and worſhip the true God only, and that in Spirit, and in Truth And again; <hi>Zephan.</hi> 2.11. <hi>The Lord will be terrible unto them, for he will famiſh all the Gods of the Earth, and men ſhall worſhip him every one from his place, even all the Iſles of the Heathen; i.e.</hi> God will aboliſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the Idols and falſe Deities of the Heathen, and all Nations ſhall be reduced to the worſhip of the true God, the Creator of Heaven and Earth, every one in his own Land; ſo that men ſhall not need to go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or be obliged to worſhip God here or there, but (as Chriſt ſpeaks) the true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit, and in Truth. And more plainly yet in Zech. 13.2. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, ſaith the Lord of Hiſts, that I will cut off the names of the Idols out of the Land, and they ſhall no more be remembred; and alſo I will cauſe the Prophets and the unclean Spirit to paſs out of the Land.</hi> And that this unclean Spirit, which ſollicited mankind to ſpiritual whoredome and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, was chaſed out of all thoſe parts of the world where the Goſpel was preached by the Apoſtles and their immediate Succeſſors, is evident; not only from Eccleſiaſtical ſtory, but from the complaints of the Heathen, that ſince the Religion of Jeſus prevailed, their Oracles were ſilent, and their Sacrifices were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62067:5"/>offer'd in vain to their phantaſtick Deities. And that this was a main deſign of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, he himſelf aſſures us in his diſcourſe with the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Joh. 4.21, 22, 23, 24. where when the Woman told our Saviour, that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> worſhipped in Mount <hi>Ephraim</hi> at <hi>Shiloh,</hi> but that the
<hi>Jews</hi> taught that God was to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped only at <hi>Jeruſalem; v.</hi> 20. He replies, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, believe me, the hour comes when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>worſhip the Father. Ye worſhip ye know not what; we know what we worſhip, for Salvation is of the</hi> Jews. <hi>But the hour comes, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit, and in Truth; for the Father ſeeks ſuch to worſhip him. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit, and in Truth.</hi> The moſt genuine Interpretation of which-ſeems to be given by that pious and learned Perſon Mr. <hi>Mede, viz.</hi> that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> who worſhipped in the Temple of Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> though they worſhipped the true God, yet it was under the viſible repreſentation of a Dove, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed their Children in the name thereof; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſays Chriſt) <hi>ye worſhip ye know not what; i.e.</hi> ye worſhip the God of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> indeed, but 'tis under a Corporeal Repreſentation, which is an argument you do not know him; but God muſt be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Spirit, and in Truth; that is, conceiving him as a Spirit, and not under any viſible ſhape. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Idolatry is a belying God, and Idols are termed lyes, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.4. — <hi>Their lyes cauſed them to err.</hi> — And Jer.
16.19. <hi>Surely our Fathers have inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lyes, the</hi> Chaldee, <hi>have worſhipped a lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62067:6"/> Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour coming into the world to correct what was amiſs, and to reform the manners of mankind, and to introduce a more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Religion than the Jewiſh was, it is not to be thought but he would in the firſt place deſign the Eradication of Idolatry, which ſo much debaſes the ſoul of man, and diſhonours the Supreme Deity, by repreſenting him in a groſs and material way, and likewiſe by giving his Incommunicable Excellencies and Perfections to a Creature. Sure it is, the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians retained ſo clear and vigorous a ſenſe of the heynouſneſs of this ſin, and the perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency of it with the ſpirituality of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that they choſe rather to endure all manner of torments, and die a thouſand deaths, than in the leaſt manner pollute their ſouls with ſo groſs an immorality. Pertinent hereunto is that obſervation which is made, that in the firſt part of the Jewiſh <hi>Talmud,</hi> which was made about 200 years after Chriſt, there is no accuſation or complaint brought againſt the Chriſtians for this Idolatry of <hi>Image-worſhip:</hi> but in the ſecond part, which was finiſhed about the year
500. when the Church of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Paganize, there, and in all the Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the
<hi>Rabbins</hi> publiſhed in the Tenth or Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Age, the Jews call the Chriſtian Churches
<hi>the Houſes of Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being plain then that Chriſt Jeſus came to era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate Idolatry, which both ſpoiled the nature of the ſoul by ſinking it into matter, and fearfully diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured the true and ever-living God; I come now to ſhew wherein the Pagan Idolatry chiefly conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was in theſe two things: 1. In worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62067:6"/>other inferiour Gods together with the true God; theſe lower ſort of Gods being looked upon as a kind of middle Beings or Mediators between the Supreme God and them: And 2. In worſhipping both the ſupreme and ſubordinate Gods in Images and Statues: That the Pagans acknowledged the true God, the Maker of Heaven and Earth; but that their Errour was in worſhipping more ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Beings together with him, and both the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and Inferiour Gods in Images, Statues, or Symbols, is the conſtant Opinion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who being the only Nation before Chriſtianity that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Heathen Polytheiſm and Idolatry, were moſt likely to underſtand the ground and bottom of it. I find two quotations cited by an eminently learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon out of two <hi>Jewiſh Rabbins,</hi> which do give us fully and excellently the ſenſe and notion of the <hi>Jews</hi> concerning the Pagan Idolatry. The firſt is out of <hi>Maimonides;</hi>
               <q>You know that whoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Idolatry, he doth it not as ſuppoſing that there is no other God beſides that which he worſhips, for it never came into the minds of any Idolaters, nor never will, that that Statue which is made by them of Metal, or Stone, or Wood, is that very God who created Heaven and Earth; but they worſhip thoſe Statues and Images only as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of ſomething which is a Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them.</q> The other is one
<hi>Moſes Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belda;</hi>
               <q>The Idolaters firſt argued thus (ſays he) in reſpect of God; that ſince he was of ſuch tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Perfection above men, it was not poſſible for men to be united to, or have communion with him, otherwiſe than by means of certain middle
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62067:7"/>Beings or Mediators; as it is the manner of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings to have Petitions conveyed to them by the hands of Mediators and Interceſſors. Secondly, they thus argued likewiſe in reſpect of themſelves, that being Corporeal, ſo that they could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God abſtractly, they muſt needs have ſomething ſenſible to excite and ſtir up their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and fix their Imagination upon.</q> The very ſame cover (as I ſhall ſhew afterwards) with which the Papiſts would palliate their Polytheiſm and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry: For the Devil has only ſhifted the Scene, and that Apoſtacy of the ſons of men which he could no longer uphold under open and broad-fac'd Paganiſm, he ſtill ſucceſsfully manages under the unmeet cover of the plauſible name of Chriſtianity. But we need not relye upon theſe Teſtimonies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, ſince S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms the ſame of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that they were not unacquainted with the knowledge of the true God; but that their great miſcarriage conſiſted in worſhipping many inferiour Gods, and then in worſhipping the true God, and all thoſe other created and dependent Deities in Statues and Images: That God left not himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out witneſs in the moſt barbarous parts of the world, but furniſhed all mankind with ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, as might and ought to have kept them from all ſorts of Idolatry, if they had been faithful to the light and natural inſcriptions of their own ſouls, appears from <hi>Rom.</hi>
1.21. <hi>When they knew God, they glorified him not as God,</hi> becauſe they fell into Polytheiſm and Idolatry. And alſo <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>That which might be known of God was manifeſt within them, God having ſhewed it unto them.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62067:7"/>
               <hi>i. e.</hi> that of God which is knowable, his Eternal Power and Godhead, with the Attributes belonging thereunto, is made manifeſt to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from his works. In which places 'tis evident, that the Pagan Nations were never deſtitute of the knowledge of the true God; and that this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was not ſome obſcure glimmering, but ſuch a clear knowledge of his Eternal Power and Godhead, as might have kept them (had it not been their own fault) from Polytheiſm and Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Now that the Heathens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> worſhipped many ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate and inferiour Gods together with the true God; that is, that they joyned Creature-worſhip with the worſhip of the Creator, the ſame Apoſtle ſays expreſly, <note place="margin">V. 25.</note> 
               <hi>they worſhipped the Creature more than the Creator:</hi> which words are not ſo to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as if the Pagans transferred their Religious worſhip wholly upon the Creature, the Creator in the mean time being altogether paſſed by; but thus, They worſhipped the Creature <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, beſides the Creator; or elſe, They worſhipped the Creature above or more than the Creator: as
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed comparatively, ſo as to ſignifie exceſs; as <hi>Luk.</hi>
13.2. &amp; 4. <hi>Think ye that theſe</hi> Galileans <hi>were ſinners</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>above all the</hi> Galileans? <hi>and ſinners</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>above all men?</hi> According to either of which Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations it is ſuppoſed, that the
<hi>Pagans</hi> did worſhip the true God, the Creator of the world, though they worſhipped the Creature alſo beſides him, or (perhaps in ſome ſenſe) above him, and more than him alſo. Which latter Interpretation I have the rather added, becauſe it ſuits ſo well with that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiouſly <hi>Paganical</hi> practice of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62067:8"/>in their worſhip of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to whom they put up ten prayers for one directed to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance we have in <hi>Act.</hi> 17. where S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the
<hi>Athenians,</hi> that as he beheld their ſacred Monuments, he found an Altar with this Inſcription, <hi>To the unknown God;</hi> and upon this adds, <hi>whom therefore you ignorantly worſhip</hi> (that is, under the name of the unknown God) <hi>him declare I unto you, the God that made the world, and all things in it, the Lord of Heaven and Earth.</hi> From whence it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; 1. That by the unknown God, was meant the true God, the Creator of all things. 2. That thoſe <hi>Pagans</hi> did religiouſly worſhip the true God. Afterwards the Apoſtle citing a paſſage out of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> cenſures their ſottiſhneſs, in giving Religious worſhip to an Image made of Gold or Silver, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the true and ever-living God in ſome Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Symbol.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Secondly, this Divine Nature which God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to form in men by the Goſpel, conſiſting in a very great meaſure in the purity and holineſs of their ſpirits, our Lord Jeſus does by all means diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance all manner of ſin and evil, faithfully declaring to all the world the Mind and Pleaſure of God herein; and aſſuring us, that whoever will be happy, muſt likewiſe be holy: That the Chriſtian Diſpenſation, which is Gods laſt and only Method which he has made known for the ſalvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, is ſo far from palliating mens Corruptions, or giving them a liberty and indulgence to ſin, that it moſt ſtrictly prohibits all, even the leaſt kind of vice and iniquity, and commands an Univerſal Holineſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62067:8"/>to run through all our Actions. And that we may not expoſe and betray our ſelves to ruine and miſery, by vain conceits and imaginations; either that an External and Phariſaical Righteouſneſs will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, or if it muſt be otherwiſe, that yet we are not bound up to ſuch ſtrict Meaſures as the common Preachers of Religion perſwade us; we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that our Lord Jeſus going on with that great Work of the Efformation of the ſacred Life and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God in Mens Souls, it would not be in any wiſe ſuitable and agreeable with his Deſign to make them only externally righteous and holy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an inward change of Mind and Diſpoſition; and therefore expreſly informs all his Followers and Diſciples, <hi>That except their Righteouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, they ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that he hath ſet the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments of rational Souls at a higher Pitch, than ever was, or could be warranted by the Doctrines and Practice of the Scribes and Phariſees; and now requires not only an abſtinence from the outward and groſs Acts of Sin, but a hearty and ſincere Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Soul from all Vice, and the Reduction of all its Powers and Faculties into an Univerſal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance to God's holy Will. By which likewiſe that falſe and carnal Liberty, which ſome would aſſume to themſelves, is wholly deſtroyed, and we are taught that Religion gives no allowance, or toleration to any the leaſt evil: that without Holineſs no Man ſhall ever ſee the Lord; and that the Promiſe of ſeeing God is only made to the Pure in Heart. Nor can we underſtand leſs by this Holineſs and Purity of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62067:9"/>Heart, than ſuch a vital Frame and Temper of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as does not only exclude all groſs Defilements and Pollutions of the Fleſh, but likewiſe all ſecret Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Combinations of Hypocrifie, and all thoſe other more ſpiritual Sins, whoſe Acts have no ſuch intimate Conjunction and Commerce with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Nay, ſo far is the Goſpel of the Son of God from countenancing, or giving any Diſpenſation to Sin, that it ſtrictly commands us to abſtain from all appearance of Evil. For he came into the World to cleanſe our Minds from all irregular and diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſts and Paſſions, and to <hi>redeem us from all Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> that is, not only from this or that particular Vice, but from all manner of Evil; to the end <hi>he might purifie unto himſelf a Peculiar People, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good works,</hi> as we read,
<hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. Sin and Evil is not a meer fantaſtick Being, an aiery No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſound of Words, but a real Nature and ſtate of Defilement and Pollution; and while the Soul is under its Dominion, it is then ſaid in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be clothed in filthy Garments: But the true Clothing of the Soul is Righteouſneſs and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.3, 4.</note> and this is compared by the Spirit of God to fine Linen, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi>
19.8.</note> clean and white.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, the Flower and Summity of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature which our Lord and Saviour came to beget in Mankind being an Univerſal Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it is certain he does not only teach it by his Commands and Example; but he condemns the contrary ſtate and temper of Mind; as directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Excellency and Perfections of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God. There is no one thing that ever our Saviour ſo earneſtly preſs'd upon his Diſciples as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62067:9"/>Love. It is his new, and his old, and laſt Command, that we love one another; and he propoſes his own Example for our Imitation — <hi>Love one another, as I have loved you.</hi> Now, How is that? Surely, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.34.</note> with a Love ſtronger than the Bands of Death, which made him give his Life a Ranſom for the World. And this alone he tells us ſhall be the Badge and Cognizance, by which his followers ſhall be known:
<hi>By this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if if ye have love one to another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 35.</note> For indeed there is nothing makes us more God-like, nor is there any thing that ſo fully expreſſes the Nature of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Being as Love; <hi>God is Love,</hi> ſays St. <hi>John.</hi> Love is the Firſt-born of Heaven, and the joy of Angels and holy Souls, whoſe pure minds never ſhine with ſo great a ſplendor and glory, as when they are irradiated with the powerful Influence of ſo ſacred a Being. Behold the grand Exemplar of Charity, the Son of God himſelf made a Man; and conſider him in all his abaſements, his ſolitudes and ſufferings, from the firſt moment of his Birth to his dying on the Croſs, and we ſhall find very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſtrong Emanations of dear Compaſſion and Benignity to the World. He was ſo far from grieving or paining or injuring any, that he went about every day doing them good, freeing them from their miſeries, and eaſing them of their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows. He never did the leaſt hurt or harm to any Man living, but rebuked the indiſcreet Zeal of his Diſciples, who would have burned the <hi>Samaritans</hi> with Fire from Heaven for denying to their Lord an Hoſpitable entertainment; adding that he came not to deſtroy, but to ſave the lives of Men. This is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62067:10"/>the Grand Law of the whole Creation, that conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidates and holds together all the parts of Heaven and Earth, and makes them conſpire in a ſweet and univerſal Harmony and Conſent; and permeating and touching humane ſouls by a vital Energy, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnates and fills them with a ſacred life: which life is no ſteril and inactive Principle, but diffuſes it ſelf in acts of dear kindneſs and benignity to all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable ſubjects, and eſpecially to Man, a Creature moſt dear to God himſelf; for whom every one that throughly partakes of this ſpirit of love, will be ready to offer up even his own life; according as the Beloved Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Hereby perceive we the love of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.16.</note>
               <hi>becauſe he laid down his life for us; and we ought to lay down our lives for the Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Having ſeen the Grand Ends and Purpoſes of God in the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, I ſhall now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt how perfectly all theſe are fruſtrated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by thoſe Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are either eſtabliſhed by Papal Laws and Statutes, or countenanced, approved and maintained with great vigour and induſtry by the Members of that Church: by which it will likewiſe appear, that the old Polytheiſm and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Heathens is really revived, eſtabliſhed and practiſed there, though in another, and newer Garb and Dreſs.</p>
            <p>In the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> place then I have declared, that the great End and Deſign of God in the Evangelical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation, was to form his own bleſſed Nature in the hearts of men, to conſummate his Holy Image, and to regenerate them by his own Spirit. And would you think that any Company or Society of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62067:10"/>men, that profeſs to be the Servants of Chriſt Jeſus, to advance his Crown and Dignity, and to ſeek the Amplification and Enlargement of his Kingdom, ſhould yet be ſo treacherous as to undermine this Grand Purpoſe, and maintain ſuch Doctrines as do directly evacuate and deſtroy, and are clearly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Mind and Will of God in the Goſpel? Behold then ſuch as are taught and allowed by the moſt eminent and leading men in the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; I ſhall inſtance only in theſe three, which are ſo notorious, and ſo diametrically oppoſite to the very end and intent of God in the Goſpel, as if by thoſe the Devil had plotted the utter extirpation and ſubverſion of that bleſſed Nature which ought of right to have the Soveraign Rule and Dominion over all Intellectual Beings. 1. The Doctrine of the Direction of the Intention. 2. The Doctrine of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability. 3. That of Sacerdotal Abſolution upon Confeſſion at the hour of Death.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Direction of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, ſerves to ſo many excellent purpoſes for the propagation of all manner of Vice, and the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into act all the ſecret machinations and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of evil, with the ſafety and ſecurity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that at firſt ſight it looks like a Deviliſh En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, fram'd on purpoſe for the deſtruction of the true and living Nature of God in mens ſouls. For if this Doctrine be true (and if it be not, let them look to it that teach and uphold it) there is no Vice ſo heynous, no Sin ſo great, but a man may <hi>ſalva Conſcientia</hi> with a good and honeſt Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, if he have but the wit to direct his Intention aright; <hi>Ex. gr.</hi> If a certain company of men here
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62067:11"/>plotted to kill the King, and ſome of them be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and brought before a Civil Magiſtrate who has Power to take the buſineſs into Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the reſt that remain yet undiſcovered may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kill both the Magiſtrate and the Witneſſes that informed againſt their Aſſociates, always provided they direct their Intention aright; for that ſecures the Action from being Criminal: that is, they muſt not kill them upon pure Revenge, for that is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Law of God, but may diſpatch them to preſerve their Reputation, or to free a whole Order and Society of men from an indelible diſgrace that is likely to be caſt upon them: and now the ſin is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and the Conſcience clean and white, as in the day of Innocence. But in ſuch an affair as this, or ſomething elſe of like nature, care muſt be taken that the Action be managed with the greateſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie; for though the inner man be ſecure, yet the outer is not; and though the Fathers Conſcience be entire and ſound, yet his Neck may be broken by the force of a Humane Law, that takes no notice of this Admirable Invention of the Direction of the Intention. In like manner this ſuperpolitick device ſhall ſanctifie and hallow Fornication, Adultery, Theft, or whatever other enormous wickedneſs a ſenſual perſon thinks fit to run into; by which all endeavours and hopes of attaining to a new Birth unto Righteouſneſs are utterly ſtifled and cut off, and the new Creature in the Scripture ſhall be no more than an empty ſound. For ſurely that Perſon can give but a poor ſign of the Renovation of his Mind, and the change of his Soul by the Spirit of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, that can allow himſelf
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62067:11"/>in any of thoſe forementioned groſs ſins, let his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> be what it will. And though perhaps it may be ſaid, that this is no Doctrine of the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, yet it is a Doctrine which is taught and practis'd by the greateſt Caſuiſts and moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Order that that Church abounds withal: Nay, it is a thing that ſeems to pervade and run through the whole Body of their Religion; foraſmuch as no Sacrament can be valid and efficacious, if the Prieſts intention be either wanting, or otherwiſe imployed. And ſince this is ſo, I ſee no reaſon why this Engine ſhould not be turned, and made to do execution upon themſelves: For ſuppoſing this to be true, it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently follows, that no man can be aſſured that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe many Millions which make up the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Hierarchy, there is ſo much as one true Prieſt, and conſequently no man can have any certainty that ever any Sacrament is rightly and duly adminiſtred: for this depends upon the mans being a true Prieſt; and that no man can know, and be ſure of, unleſs he firſt be certain that he was rightly and duly bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; nor can he have any aſſurance of this, unleſs he be likewiſe certain that he was baptized with due Intention; that is, that the Miniſter of his Baptiſm was not a ſecret <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Moor,</hi> or
<hi>Atheiſt,</hi> but a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in heart as well as Profeſſion; (otherwiſe believing the Sacrament to be nothing, in giving it he could intend to give nothing) and that he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of negligence nor malice omitted his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. But ſuppoſe the man be a true Prieſt, yet when he conſecrates the Sacrament, I am not ſure he will do it with Intention; for there is a ſtory of a Prieſt that was burnt in <hi>France</hi> for compacting with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62067:12"/>the Devil, to give no Sacraments with Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Doctrine of Probability is likewiſe a neat and excellent Device to ſet forward the Trade of Sin and Wickedneſs: For thus <hi>Emanuel Sa, A man may do what he conceives lawful, according to a probable Opinion, though the contrary be more ſafe.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to this is the Aſſertion of the Jeſuit <hi>Knot</hi> in Mr. <hi>Chillingworth, That for the avoiding of ſin, we are not always bound to take the ſafeſt way, but may follow the Opinion of any probable Doctors.</hi> Which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Doctrine is loaded with ſo many miſchievous and fatal conſequences, as render that new Birth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Righteouſneſs, without which our Saviour ſays no man ſhall enter into Heaven, perfectly uſeleſs and unneceſſary. For 1. From hence it will follow, that a man may reſolve not to uſe his utmoſt care and endeavour to avoid ſin, without any hazard or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his damnation: And if this Doctrine be once throughly reduced to practice in the lives of men, a deluge and flood of wickedneſs will as certainly break in and overflow the World, as the waters once drowned it when God broke up the Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes of Heaven and Earth: For this caſts a fatal damp upon all endeavours after Holineſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and mens Zeal and Contention for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate of life cools like the air by intervening ſhowres, and all thoſe Motives and Exhortations which are uſed in the Goſpel to excite and ſtir up our drowſie ſouls to a watchful and diligent proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the War againſt ſin are rebated and made ineffectual, and the Fire of Hell is no more to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued than a painted flame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62067:12"/> Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> diſcourſing upon this Doctrine, of probability, ſays, <note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note> He knew a young Scholar in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> Licens'd by a great Caſuiſt, to ſwear a thing as upon his certain knowledge, whereof he had yet no knowledge but only a great preſumption, becauſe (forſooth) it was the opinion of one Doctor he might do ſo. Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> teaches, That want of Power to maintain a Rebellion, was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reaſon that the Primitive Chriſtians did not rebel againſt the Perſecuting Emperours. To whom agrees <hi>Aquinas,</hi> when he ſays, <hi>Eccleſiam toleraſſe ut fideles obedirent Juliano Apoſtatae, quia ſui novitate nondum habebant vires compeſcendi Principes terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> i. e. That the Church ſuffered the faithful to obey
<hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, becauſe by their late riſe they had not ſufficient ſtrength to repreſs Earthly Princes. Here are two Probable Doctors, and the concluſion from thence is, that when ever they find themſelves to have a Party ſtrong enough, they may (having the Opinion of ſuch Probable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors on their ſide) attempt the Murder of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Prince, and introduce their Religion, though with the Blood of thouſands of innocent Perſons: And this they may do, although themſelves ſhould think it unlawful, becauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and
<hi>Aquinas,</hi> Men of approved Virtue and Learning among them, have determined for the lawfulneſs of it. 2. From hence it will follow, that a Man may forſake the more ſafe and infallible Direction of Gods Word, and the clear Evidence of Reaſon and Conſcience, and take up with the Opinion of ſome one Man, who perhaps ſpeaks unadviſedly and careleſly; or it may be out of deſign and ſet purpoſe to deceive:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62067:13"/>and by this means all the ſevere Duties of Religion ſhall be evacuated, and the Precepts of the Goſpel made to comply with the Vices and corrupt Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men, and all as it pleaſes our Probable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: which certainly is the moſt unreaſonable and unrighteous Uſurpation upon the underſtandings of Mankind that ever was; as if the generality of Men were made only to be impoſed upon: Nay, by this means the beſt and wholſomeſt Laws in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World ſhall be reſcinded, if there be but a Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctor to diſpute their Obligation.</p>
            <p>Theſe horrid and impious Conſequences will yet appear more plain and evident by thoſe Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Firſt, we are commanded in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to love the Lord our God with all our heart, with all our ſoul, and with all our ſtrength; and the truth and ſincerity of our love is evidenced by avoiding of Sin, and by keeping his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But now if a Man may forſake the plain and eaſie direction of God in the ſacred Writings, and reſt in the Opinion of a Probable Doctor, he need not much trouble his Head about the love of God.
<note place="margin">See the Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm.</note> 
               <hi>Hurtado de Mendoza</hi> (as he is cited by Father <hi>Eſcobar</hi>) ſays, A Man is bound but once every year to have an actual affection for God. <hi>Coninck</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes we are bound to it once in three or four years:
<hi>Henriquez,</hi> once in five years: But <hi>Filiutius</hi> thinks a Man is not obliged every five years. And if we do not think our ſelves fairly dealt withal yet, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Syrmond</hi> will make a full amends, and he aſſures us we need not love God at all; <hi>For we are not ſo much commanded</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to love God, as not to hate him.</hi> Secondly, we are injoined a ſpeedy and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62067:13"/>ſincere Repentance in the holy Scriptures, to turn from our Sins and Impieties unto God, <hi>while 'tis called to day,</hi> that is, to make uſe of the preſent time which is only ours. But if throwing the Scripture aſide, we may without danger follow the Guidance of any Probable Doctor, then a Man is bound to repent only three times a year, at
<hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide;</hi> for ſo <hi>Scotus</hi> ſays: But if you are unwilling to undergo this burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and afflictive Duty ſo often, you need perform it but once a year; and for this you have the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Scotus</hi> and <hi>Medina.</hi> And if you think this too much, hear what <hi>Reginaldus</hi> ſays, <hi>The time when a Man is bound to repent, is, at the Article of imminent Death; for the mean while there is no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept commanding that a Sinner ſhould not perſevere in enmity againſt God: there is no Negative Precept for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding ſuch a Perſeverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How directly repugnant thoſe Doctrines are to that Grand Poſitive end of the Goſpel, the Replan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ſacred Image and Nature of God in the Souls of Men, every pious Chriſtian, who earneſtly deſires the Recovery of the World from the Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlavery of Sin, cannot but ſee; and that thoſe Champions which the Dark Kingdom ſet out to defend and maintain the
<hi>Pagan</hi> Worſhip (which quickly vaniſhed and diſappeared in all places where Chriſtianity ſhone in its Native luſtre and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) were not half ſo ſucceſsful in their Attempts, nor ſuch dangerous Enemies of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, as thoſe Popiſh Agents, who by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyes in Hypocriſie do really Debauch and Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the World again, and make Men two-fold more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62067:14"/>the Children of Hell, than if they had been perfect Strangers to the very name of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Doctrine which undermines the Grand Purpoſe of God Almighty in regenerating and renewing the World by the Goſpel, is that of <hi>Sacerdotal Abſolution</hi> upon Confeſſion at the hour of death: For thus the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teach,
<hi>That though a man live and die without the practice of Chriſtian Virtues, and with the habits of many damnable ſins unmortified, yet if he in the laſt moment of his life have any ſorrow for his ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligw.</hi> Ch. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and joyn Confeſſion with it, he ſhall certainly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> Which is a Doctrine, that inſtead of reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bettering the World (which certainly was intended by the manifeſtation of the Goſpel) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens a door to all imaginable licentiouſneſs and wickedneſs. Our bleſſed Saviour aſſures us, that <hi>except a man be born again, he ſhall not enter into Heaven:</hi> Now certain it is, that Divine Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as well as Natural, are not inſtantaneous, but require time for their full maturity and perfection; and as ſure is it, that an Act of Attrition, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with <hi>Sacerdotal Abſolution,</hi> can never work a change or Renovation of the mind; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, it muſt be as horrid a Cheat as ever was put upon the poor deluded Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them that this is enough for their Salvation, though otherwiſe they die without the practice of Chriſtian Virtues, and with the habits of many damnable ſins unmortified. For, to ſpeak the plain truth, this kind of Abſolution looks more like a Charm or Spell, uſed by ſuperſtitious people to fright away evil ſpirits, than any thing of ſober
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62067:14"/>truth, having neither Reaſon nor Scripture to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or abett it. And though men may deceive and befool one another, yet thoſe unhappy people, whoſe ſad Fate it is to be ſent out of the world with no better hopes of Salvation, than what an Act of Attrition with Prieſtly Abſolution is able to give them, will find the Scene of Affairs quite altered there, and thoſe grim Officers of the Infernal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will infallibly challenge and ſeize their own, notwithſtanding the faireſt diſmiſſion by all the arts and devices of a treacherous Ghoſtly Father. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider all you that have any care for your Eternal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Salvation, how groſly you are abuſed by theſe Holy Impoſtors and Factors for the Devils Kingdom! Can the Abſolution of your Prieſt work a real change in your Diſpoſitions and Natures? or can thoſe few words effect a Mortification of your vicious habits, and withal ſuperinduce the contrary Virtues? Will this Charm procure a ſafe paſſage through the Guards of the inviſible Regions? or ſhall your Wonder-working Prieſt give you an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Heaven, when the expreſs Declarations of Chriſt Jeſus exclude you thence? No wonder that
<hi>Papiſts</hi> have their Prieſts in ſuch high eſteem and Veneration; no marvel they declare they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live without them, when they are endued with ſuch an Omnipotency as to change the ſetled order of things, to alter the Decrees of Heaven, and cancel the fixed Laws of life and death, by ſhutting them out of the preſence of God, whom Chriſt Jeſus is ready to receive, and intromitting others that he has declared ſhall be for ever baniſhed thence.
<hi>But be not deceived, God is not mocked; for whatever a man
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62067:15"/>ſows, that ſhall he alſo reap: He that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption; but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Hitherto in general I have ſhewed the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Popiſh Doctrines to the Grand End and Purpoſe of God in the Goſpel; I ſhall now deſcend to the particulars afore-mentioned; the firſt of which was this, that in order to the replantation of the Divine Nature in the ſouls of men, Almighty God deſigned the utter extirpation of Idolatry. Now though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> endeavours by many fine ſhows and ſpecious pretences to free her ſelf from the imputation of ſo foul and horrid a Crime, yet he that impartially weighs things, ſhall find her no leſs guilty than was the Pagan World before the coming of Chriſt. And if this do not evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to every candid and ingenious Reader, I am well aſſured, that
'tis not from the weakneſs or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concluſiveneſs of the Arguments, but from ſome partial and preconceived Opinion, or ſome other prejudice his mind labours under, and is prepoſſeſſed and preingaged withal: for this I do confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that there is no truth of greater uſefulneſs and concernment to Reformed Chriſtendom, nor any that can more clearly and irrefragably juſtifie the neceſſity of our ſeparation from that Church than this.</p>
            <p>That I may therefore make a clear and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative proof of this Charge which I have laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, I muſt a little recur to what I have ſaid of the Pagan Idolatry, which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſted in theſe two things: 1. In that they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62067:15"/>worſhipped (beſides one Supreme God) other Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Beings, not as independent and ſelf-exiſtent, but as ſo many created Deities: and theſe were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by them upon theſe two accounts, either as thinking that the honour done to them redounded to the Supreme, or elſe that they might be their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators and Interceſſors, Orators and Negotiators with him. 2. In that they worſhipped both the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God, and likewiſe their ſubordinate Deities in Images and Statues.</p>
            <p>This Foundation being laid, it will be no difficult task to draw the parallel between the ancient Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Idolatry, and that now practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> That the Saints and Angels are worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped both publickly and privately in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, needs no other teſtimony than the daily practice of Papiſts, who expreſs a greater fervour and zeal in their Invocation of the Saints, than of God himſelf: ſo that as a learned Perſon obſerves, <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop. Spec.</note> for one prayer to God, they put up ten to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Nay, ſo mad are they after this extravagant humour, that <hi>Caſſander</hi> ingeniouſly confeſſes, that ſome, and thoſe no bad men, have made choice of ſome certain Saints as their Patrons, and place their truſt and confidence in their Merits and Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, more than in the Merits of Chriſt; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſſand.</hi> Conſult. do Invoc. Sanct.</note> and ſo lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide the Mediation of Chriſt, they have ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the Saints, and eſpecially the Virgin
<hi>Mary</hi> in his room. And hence Cardinal <hi>Hoſius</hi> is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſay, <hi>We ought to believe in the Saints.</hi> They build Temples and Altars to the Saints, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelves with the moſt humble devotion before their Images. They ſwear by the Saints, not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62067:16"/>only in their common ſpeech, but in their more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oaths, and to them they direct their Vows likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Now upon the ſame accounts that the Pagans worſhipped their inferiour Deities, do the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore and worſhip the Saints and Angels. 1. Becauſe the honour done to them redounds to God himſelf: It is for the Majeſty and Grandeur of the ſupreme God to have a multitude of inferiour Deities under him, ſays <hi>Plotinus:</hi> It is not only ſuitable with the bountiful and noble diſpoſition of God not to grant many graces and favours but by the Interceſſion of the Saints, but likewiſe for his glory that the world ſhould know this, <note place="margin">Anſwer to certain Queſtions propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by King <hi>James.</hi>
               </note> ſays
<hi>Fiſher</hi> the Jeſuit; which he further illuſtrates by this ſimilitude, becauſe (ſays he) 'tis impoſſible to honour and praiſe the Boughs, without honouring and praiſing the Root; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Saints and Angels are invocated and adored, it is for the honour of the ſupreme God, the Root and Spring of all things. 2. They make them Mediators and Interceſſors between God and them; which was the office and imployment of the <hi>Mediae Poteſtates,</hi> or middle Deities of the Heathen; and the ground or reaſon of this is given by S. <hi>Auſtin, becauſe they excel us Mortals in Merits.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Civ. Dei, lib. <hi>8. c. 22.</hi>
               </note> And that the Papiſts urge the Merits of their Saints, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from divers of their publick forms of prayer: The Saints are in high grace and favour with God, and for this reaſon we poor Mortals implore their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, ſay the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> as we make uſe of a Courtier to deliver a Petition to an Earthly Prince. After this manner
<hi>Celſus</hi> argues, when he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Chriſtians to the worſhip of
<hi>Daemons,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62067:16"/>that they ought to ſeek their favour as the Miniſters of the Great God: To whom <hi>Origen</hi> replies, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen</hi> contr. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, l.
<hi>8.</hi>
               </note> that the Chriſtians allow indeed an honour and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the bleſſed Angels as Gods Miniſters in a ſound ſenſe, but they are taught to give Religious Worſhip only to God, and to his Son, his Word and Image, by whom they offer up their Supplications to God the Lord of all, beſeeching him who is the Propitiation for our ſins, that he would be pleaſed, as our High-Prieſt, to offer up our Prayers, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and Interceſſions to the great God. And again, God alone is to be adored, and our Prayers are only to be offered to the only begotten Word of God, the Firſt-born of every Creature, who as our High-Prieſt offers our Supplications to his God, and our God, to his Father, and the Father of all thoſe that live according to his Word. But if the favour of many be to be ſought for, we learn from the Scriptures, that thouſand thouſands miniſter unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, who afford their friendly aſſiſtance to thoſe that humbly invoke the Supreme God, and earneſtly contend after Salvation, diſdaining not to be officious to them that worſhip the ſame God with themſelves: For as the Shadow follows the Body as it moves; ſo when any perſon hath God propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to him, at the ſame time all the Angels and bleſſed Spirits are likewiſe his Friends. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays, that God hath his Miniſters, whom we call Angels, <hi>verum hi neque Dii ſunt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Deos ſe vocari aut coli volunt; quippe qui nihil praeter juſſum ac voluntatem Dei fatiant; i. e.</hi> but theſe are neither Gods, nor would they be called
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62067:17"/>Gods, nor worſhipped; foraſmuch as they only exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Will and Command of God.</p>
            <p>Add to this, that the Papiſts make their Saints particular Preſidents and Regents of Countries, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Religious Orders, of Beaſts, and of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Fire, Water,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and appoint to them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and by name ſeveral Opitulations. So
<hi>Caeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> in <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> ſays of the Heathens, that each particular Nation had its own Municipal Gods which they worſhipped: And <hi>Arnobius</hi> tells the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> adver. Gentes.</note> that with them <hi>Dii certi certas habent tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telas, licentias, poteſtates, neque eorum ab aliquo id quod ejus non ſit poteſtatis ac licentiae poſtulant; i. e.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gods have certain Guardianſhips, Licences and Powers; neither do they ask from any of them that which is not in their power and gift. Accordingly the Papiſts have diſtributed ſeveral Offices to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Saints, whoſe aſſiſtance they implore for thoſe particular things to which they are appointed: as for example, S. <hi>Apollonia</hi> for the Tooth-ach, S. <hi>Otilia</hi> for Bleer-Eyes, S.
<hi>Rochus</hi> for the Pox, S. <hi>Blaſius</hi> for the Squinancy, S. <hi>Petronella</hi> for Feavers, S. <hi>Wende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> for Sheep and Oxen, S. <hi>Anthony</hi> for Hogs, S.
<hi>Nicholas</hi> is the Patron of Mariners, S. <hi>Clement</hi> of Bakers, S. <hi>Luke</hi> of Painters, and S. <hi>Afra</hi> and <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> of Whores. For S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, that <hi>Varro</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <note place="margin">C. D. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> it was profitable to know the power and working of every God in particular, that men might be able to ſue unto them according to their ſeveral Offices for every diſtinct or particular bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, leſt otherwiſe they might ask water of <hi>Bacchus</hi> the God of Wine, or Wine of the Nymphs the Goddeſſes of the Water. And this is ſo plain and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62067:17"/>evident, that it could not but extort this honeſt Confeſſion from
<hi>Ludovicus Vives,</hi> one of their own; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Com.</hi> C. D. <hi>l.</hi>
8. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Multi Chriſtiani, &amp;c.</hi> Many Chriſtians err in a good matter, in that they worſhip He<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and She-Saints after the ſame manner that they worſhip God: nor can I ſee in many things what difference there is between their Opinion of the Saints, and that which the Heathens thought of their Gods: For what other account did the Pagans make, or in what did they do honour to their inferiour Deities, which Papiſts do not expreſs to their Saints? Did the Pagans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate Temples to their Demons? ſo do the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to their Saints: Do they appropriate ſeveral offices and imployments to their inferiour Gods? the ſame do Papiſts to their Saints: Have they Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars built to them? ſo have the Saints: Do the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens offer Sacrifice to their Deities? ſo do <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> to the Saints: Had they Images erected to them? ſo have the Saints: Were the Demons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked before their Images? ſo are the Saints: Did they make Vows to the Demons? ſo do Papiſts to their Saints: Do they make thoſe Middle Powers Mediators and Interceſſors between the Supreme God and them? it is no more than what Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Saints. Now what theſe <hi>Mediae Poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> or Middle Powers were, we learn from <hi>Apulei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that they are <hi>inter terricolas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Deo <hi>Socratis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>calicolaſque Vecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, hinc precum, inde donorum, qui ultro citroque por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, hinc petitiones, inde ſuppetias, ceu quidam u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinque Interpretes &amp; Salutigeri; i. e.</hi> a kind of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers between the Inhabitants of Heaven and Earth, that travelling to and fro, carry from hence Prayers, and bring from thence Bleſſings, from hence Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62067:18"/>and Petitions, from thence ſupplies and aids; or a certain kind of Interpreters, or Meſſengers, and <hi>Internuncii</hi> between both. And 'tis a great ſign, that the more underſtanding Papiſts were long ago ſenſible of this, becauſe in their Expurgatory <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> they take ſpecial care that ſuch expreſſions as theſe ſhould be blotted and razed out of thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that ſpeak againſt their wicked Practices, <hi>viz.</hi> that God alone is to be adored, that the Saints are to be honoured, but not Religiouſly worſhipped; that Angels are not to be honoured with Religious Worſhip.</p>
            <p>And becauſe when Proteſtants cite ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly blaſphemous and idolatrous forms of prayer, allowed in the Popiſh Church, wherein they beg of their Saints, and eſpecially of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> no leſs Boons than remiſſion of ſins, preſervation from the aſſaults of the Devil, a ſafe conduct through the hazards of the World to eternal life, comfort and aſſiſtance at the hour of death, and the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Eternal Glory in the life to come: The Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Papiſts amongſt us are taught, that theſe forms of prayer are no more than an <hi>Ora pro nobis,</hi> and all one as to ſay Holy Apoſtle, or Bleſſed Lady, pray for us; (which yet is Idolatry) it is certain that many of them are made in other expreſſions, and likewiſe are direct Addreſſes to ſuch and ſuch Saints, upon account of what is peculiar for them to help them in. The prayer to S. <hi>Agnes</hi> is not <hi>Ora pro nobis,</hi> but <hi>te exoro precibus,</hi> I pray you to keep me in the right Faith, or grant you that all may ſerve God in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect charity. And the prayer to S. <hi>Brigit</hi> is, <hi>By your ſafe guidance bring us to the reward of everlaſting
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62067:18"/>life.</hi> Can any man in his right ſenſes ſay, that this is no more, then <hi>O</hi> Brigit <hi>pray for us.</hi> The <hi>Belgick</hi> Expurgatory <hi>Index</hi> commands theſe words to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed out of <hi>Fabricius</hi> (which are not much unlike this ſubterfuge of our Jeſuits) <hi>O all ye Saints pray to God for me,</hi> is all one as to ſay,
<hi>I wiſh all the Saints would pray to God for me;</hi> adding this reaſon, for in very deed we invoke the Saints, not only wiſhing, but requiring their prayers; which cannot be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Idolatry.</p>
            <p>The account which <hi>Chemnitius</hi> gives of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of this piece of Paganiſm into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, is to this purpoſe; That in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, until two hundred years after Chriſt, <note place="margin">Exam. Concil. Trident. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </note> this Doctrine and Practice was utterly unknown: then about the year 370. it began to be ſpoken of in Publick Aſſemblies by <hi>Baſil, Nyſſen,</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> upon occaſion of their Panegyrical Orations, at the ſame time when by the ſame Perſons Monkery was brought out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> into <hi>Greece.</hi> But notwithſtanding this, it was not generally and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received in thoſe times, for about the year 400. S.
<hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> interpoſed and laboured againſt it. Afterwards he ſhews out of
<hi>Nicephorus,</hi> that <hi>Petrus Gnapheus</hi> (condemned for Hereſie in the fifth Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Synod) was the firſt Author among the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> of mixing Interceſſions to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with Divine Prayers: And moreover, that in S.
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>'s days, Invocation of Saints was not uſed in the common Service of the Weſtern Church, but that it was brought in about the time of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>Nor can this Paganiſh Idolatry be palliated and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62067:19"/>excuſed by that poor Subterfuge of diſtinguiſhing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious worſhip into <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia,</hi> the firſt of which is proper only to God, the other to Creatures; that is, to Saints and Angels. Firſt, becauſe the true Object of religious worſhip is but one, for God is one; and therefore whatever Creature is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with religious worſhip, though inferiour to that which is given to the Supreme God, is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> by this made a God, ſo far as it is poſſible for a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be made a God. 2. The words
<hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> are promiſcuouſly uſed in Scripture, to denote the worſhip due to God alone, as 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Ye turned to God from Idols,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to ſerve the living, and true God:</hi> VVhich had been a Derogation if the Apoſtle had uſed a word that had ſignified any thing leſs than Divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Particular with a Paſſage which I find cited out of
<hi>Athanaſius</hi> his fourth Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the <hi>Arrians;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. Why therefore do not theſe <hi>Arrians</hi> holding this, reckon themſelves amongſt the <hi>Pagans,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſince they do in like manner worſhip the Creature, beſides the Creator? For though the <hi>Pagans</hi> worſhip one uncreated, and many created Gods; but theſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> only one uncreated, and one created, to wit, the Son, or VVord of God: yet will not this make any real difference betwixt them; becauſe the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> one created, is one of thoſe many <hi>Pagan</hi> Gods, and thoſe many Gods of the
<hi>Pagans,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> have the ſame nature with this one, they being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Creatures. Wherefore theſe wretched <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are Apoſtates from the truth of Chriſtianity, they betraying Chriſt more than the <hi>Jews</hi> did; and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62067:19"/>wallowing, or tumbling in the filth of <hi>Pagan</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, worſhipping Creatures and different kinds of Gods. In which Paſſage of this Father theſe things are obſervable; 1. That the <hi>Arrians</hi> are charged with <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry in the ſame words which St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſed againſt the <hi>Heathens, That they did worſhip the Creature, beſides, or in the room of the Creator:</hi> for the <hi>Arrians</hi> conſtantly declared that they gave leſs worſhip to Chriſt the Son, or Word of God, he being by them accounted but a Creature, than they did to the Father the Creator. 2. That the <hi>Pagan</hi> Polytheiſm and Idolatry conſiſted in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one only uncreated and independent, and many created Gods. 3. That the worſhip of the true God is not enough to excuſe from Idolatry, if any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be worſhipped with religious worſhip together with him: for then the
<hi>Pagans</hi> cannot be charged with the guilt of Idolatry. 4. That the Fathers of the
<hi>Nicene</hi> Council (if we may credit <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) affirmed, that to give religious worſhip to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Being whatſoever, though inferiour to that worſhip which is given to the Supreme God, is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Idolatry: and therefore the diſtinction of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip into <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia,</hi> as it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly unknown to them, ſo was it invented of late meerly to palliate and hide the odious Turpitude of <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry. Becauſe it is certain that the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> gave much an inferiour worſhip to Chriſt, the Son, or Word of God, whom they contended to be a meer Creature, made in time, mutable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectible, than they did to that eternal God who was the Creator of him. Now if the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who zealouſly contended for the Unity of the God-head,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62067:20"/>were nevertheleſs by thoſe Fathers condemned as guilty of <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry, for beſtowing but an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour kind of religious worſhip upon Chriſt, the Son, or Word of God himſelf, as he was ſuppoſed by them to be a Creature; then certainly cannot Papiſts be excuſed from that guilt, who beſtow reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip upon theſe other Creatures, Angels, and Souls of Men, though inferiour to what they give to the Supreme Omnipotent God the Creator of all. Becauſe the Son, or Word of God, however conceived by theſe
<hi>Arrians</hi> to be a Creature, yet was looked upon by them as the firſt, the moſt glorious, and excellent of all Creatures; and that by which, as an Inſtrument, all other Creatures, as Angels, and Souls were made: And therefore if it were Idolatry in them to give an inferiour kind of religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to this Son, and Word of God himſelf, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their
<hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> then can it not poſſibly be accounted leſs to beſtow the ſame upon thoſe other Creatures made by him, as Angels, and Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</p>
            <p>I confeſs there are many Pious and Learned Men, both of our own, and other Nations, who cannot be induced to believe that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> are <hi>Pagani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> Idolatrous in this Particular: The Grounds, and Reaſons of this their Diſſent ſeem to be theſe three eſpecially, which are laid down by <hi>Curcellaeus:</hi> 1. <hi>In the</hi> Romiſh
<hi>Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the one Supreme God, the Maker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Adrian Tatium.</note> 
               <hi>and Governour of Heaven and Earth, is acknowledged, and adored; and the Saints are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with an inferiour degree of honour as the Friends of God, and ſuch as are in great favour with him. But the</hi> Pagans <hi>were ignorant of the true God,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62067:20"/>and ſubſtituted the Sun and Moon, the Souls of dead Men and Daemons, in his place, and worſhipped them as Gods.</hi> 2. <hi>There is no doubt but the Saints and Martyrs, whom the</hi> Roman <hi>Catholicks worſhip, are worthy of ſome veneration of the Mind, for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Virtues, and conſtancy in Perſecutions. But to worſhip the Stars that have neither ſenſe nor reaſon, is ridiculous: And no honour can be due to the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Impious and Flagitious Kings, ſuch as</hi> Jupiter <hi>was: And as for Daemons, they ought to be deteſted by all good Men, as haters of God and Virtue.</hi> 3. <hi>The</hi> Romaniſts
<hi>indeed attribute to their Saints a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in ſome ſenſe and meaſure Divine, by which they hear our Prayers, and take notice of our wants and neceſſities; although the Scripture deny all ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the Dead, as</hi> Eccleſ. 9.5, 6. Job 14.21. <hi>But this doth ſomewhat leſſen their Errour, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the Saints have not this knowledge of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but from the Gift of God. But now the</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <hi>err inexcuſably, while they aſcribe to their falſe Gods an independent Knowledge and Power, which is only competible to the Supreme God. Thus far</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaeus. <hi>To which I reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt, That it is a vulgar Errour to ſuppoſe the <hi>Pagans</hi> ignorant of the true God, or that they did not worſhip the Supreme God, the Maker of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth; as not only appears from the Texts of Scripture cited already, but is clearly and evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated, by a Perſon of ſingular Learning, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s true Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, <hi>l. 1. c. 4. p. 462.</hi>
               </note> who from
<hi>Plutarch, Heraiſcus, Aſclepiades,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, affirm theſe two to be Fundamental Points of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Theology: Firſt, that there is one Self-originated Deity, who was the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Maker
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62067:21"/>of the whole VVorld. Secondly, That there are beſides him, other Gods alſo to be religiouſly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped (that is, Intellectual Beings ſuperiour to Men) which were notwithſtanding all made, or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by that one. To the Supreme God they gave the higheſt worſhip, but to thoſe ſubordinate Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they gave a leſſer, or inferiour kind of religious worſhip: that is, they adored and worſhipped the Supreme God, as the firſt Cauſe and Original of all things; but their inferiour Deities as Mediators, and Interceſſors for them with the Supreme <hi>Numen.</hi> And where I pray lies the difference now between the
<hi>Papiſt</hi> and the <hi>Pagan,</hi> ſave that the <hi>Dii Mediox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umi</hi> of the
<hi>Heathens</hi> are changed into Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels by the <hi>Papiſts?</hi> And if it be ſaid that the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> ſubſtituted theſe Subordinate Gods in the room of the Supreme God, and worſhipped them above, or more than him, I ſhall readily grant it; and do likewiſe affirm the ſame of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing religious worſhip to Saints and Angels, do real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtitute them in the place of the true God, and worſhip them above, or more than him, for ſo Sir <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> tells us, that for one Prayer put up to God, <note place="margin">Europ. ſpec.</note> there are ten offered to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> So that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are not ſo much the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the Man Chriſt Jeſus, as of the VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man his Mother. But that the <hi>Pagans</hi> did ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their inferiour Deities, as wholly to paſs by, and neglect the Supreme, I utterly deny.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond I ſay, That it is true the Saints and Martyrs are worthy of ſome regard and veneration, but not of religious worſhip, which to give them is down-right Idolatry: but the honour and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62067:21"/>which we pay to the Saints departed conſiſts, 1. In making an honourable mention of their Names, as being great and glorious Lights in their times. 2. in ſetting before our Eyes their Virtues, and praying to God to give us Grace to follow their good Examples, that with them we may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his Heavenly Kingdom. And whereas 'tis ſaid, that it was ridiculous in the <hi>Heathen</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Stars that have neither ſenſe nor reaſon; I find them utterly diſclaiming this latter part, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they looked upon all the World, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts thereof, to be animated at leaſt with one great Soul: and they that worſhipped the Sun, did not do it as ſuppoſing the Sun to be nothing but a dead and lifeleſs thing, but as animated with ſome Intellectual Being. For to deny the Worlds Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and to be an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> or to deny a God, was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by them as one and the ſame thing; becauſe all the <hi>Pagans</hi> who aſſerted Providence, held the World alſo to be animated; and <hi>Epicurus</hi> denyed the Worlds Animation upon no other Reaſon, but becauſe he Atheiſtically endeavoured to exclude a Providence. And though the Poets have introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced many abſurd and impure Fables into their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, concerning <hi>Jupiter;</hi> yet certain it is that by <hi>Jupiter</hi> the <hi>Heathens</hi> underſtood the Supreme God, the true
<hi>Etymon</hi> of <hi>Jupiter</hi> being not <hi>Juvans Pater,</hi> a helping Father, (as
<hi>Cicero</hi> would have it,) but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Pater, Jove</hi> the Father of Gods and Men; which
<hi>Jovis</hi> is the very <hi>Hebrew Tetragrammaton,</hi> only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by a <hi>Latin Termination.</hi> And <hi>Jupiter, Pluto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Cudworth, Intellect. Syſt.</hi> l. 1. c. 4. p. 451.</note> 
               <hi>Neptune, Juno, Minerva,</hi> &amp;c. in the <hi>Pagan Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> are nothing but the <hi>Polyonymy</hi> of one and the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62067:22"/>ſame Supreme Being in the various actings and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of himſelf in the ſeveral things and parts of the world. But if <hi>Jupiter</hi> were an impious King, and the Heathens worſhipped him after his death, I do not doubt but to find many ſuch Saints in the
<hi>Roman</hi> Calendar. Laſtly, for the Demons worſhipped by the Pagans, it is evident, they looked upon them under another notion, and did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them to be haters of God and Virtue, but Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators and Interceſſors, and ſuch who did negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Affairs between Mortals and the Supreme God: So that this Argument, like the former, proceeding upon a falſe ſuppoſition, leaves no other difference but what ariſes from the change of names between Papiſt and Pagan; but the Popiſh Saints are exactly like the Demons of the Heathen.</p>
            <p>To the third, which extenuates the errour of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in their Invocation of Saints, becauſe they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Omniſcience of the Saints, whereby they hear their Suppliants throughout all the World, to God as his gift; I reply, that the ſame may be ſaid of the ſubordinate Gods of the Heathens, who were altogether as Omniſcient as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Saints: Nor did the Pagans ever look upon their Middle Gods as ſo many particular independent and ſelf-originated Beings, but were acknowledged to be the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Supreme God, and made by him what they were fancied to be by their Devotioniſts; and all the honour conferred upon theſe ſubordinate Deities, was judged by the Pagans to redound to the Supreme.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Having now diſpatched the firſt part, wherein I affirmed the Pagan Polytheiſm and Idolatry to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62067:22"/>namely, in worſhipping many inferiour crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Deities together with the Supreme God, and drawn the Parallel fully and exactly between this Heatheniſh worſhip, and that now practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I ſhall with the ſame clearneſs and evidence demonſtrate the ſecond Part, <hi>viz.</hi> that Papiſts do egregiouſly Paganize in worſhipping both the Supreme God, and their other Inferiour Deities, in Images and Statues. And let not any man be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and think, that becauſe Papiſts do not call Angels and the Souls of men departed <hi>Gods,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Deities,</hi> but <hi>Saints,</hi> that therefore the caſe is quite different between them and the Pagans; for by giving Religious worſhip to them, they do for that very reaſon make them Gods, whether they call them ſo or not: for neither did the Heathens believe their inferiour Deities to be ſo many ſelf-exiſtent and independent, but created, Beings, made by the Supreme God; but by performing Religious worſhip to them, they made them Gods, ſo far as any Creature can be made a God; and upon this account they are called Gods in Scripture: ſo that I cannot free the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church from Polytheiſm and Idolatry, any more than the Pagan VVorld, who by all Chriſtian VVriters has been juſtly branded with that heynous Impiety.</p>
            <p>That the Pagans worſhipped the Supreme God, and likewiſe their ſubordinate Deities in Images and Statues, I think is ſo evident as not to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; however, I ſhall offer ſomething towards the proof of it: And firſt, that the Heathens worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the true God, the Creator of Heaven and Earth in an Image, appears from the ſtory of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62067:23"/>of <hi>Thebais,</hi> who worſhipped the Maker of VVorld under the name of
<hi>Cneph,</hi> in an Image or Statue of humane form, and a blackiſh sky-coloured complexion, holding in his hand a Girdle and a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and wearing upon his head a Princely Plume, and thruſting forth an Egg out of his mouth; and by this <hi>Cneph Plutarch</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">De Iſide.</note> they underſtood <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an unmade and Eternal Deity. But it is moſt apparent from that ſacred Hiſtory (which I touched upon before) in
<hi>Act.</hi> 17.29. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch then as we are his Off-ſpring, we ought not to think that the Godhead is like unto Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or Stone graven by art or mans device.</hi> In which words there are theſe things implyed: 1. That the <hi>Athenians</hi> worſhipped God in an Image or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; for had they not done ſo, it had been imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and beſide the Apoſtles ſcope, to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt Image-worſhip as here he does. 2. That this God to whom they built an Altar, and gave Religious worſhip, was the true God: For that that <hi>Jupiter</hi> whom <hi>Aratus</hi> invokes in his <hi>Phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and from whence S. <hi>Paul</hi> cited that paſſage— <hi>For we are his Off-ſpring</hi>—was the Supreme God, the Lord of Heaven and Earth, we are informed from <hi>Theon</hi> the Scholiaſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. We muſt underſtand (ſaith he) here by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the Maker of the World. And ſo S.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſays, that he of whom <hi>Aratus</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>We are his Off-ſpring,</hi> and whom the <hi>Athenians</hi> ignorantly worſhipped under the name of the unknown God, he it is that is the Maker and Lord of Heaven and Earth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was a very non-ſenſical and ridiculous thing to endeavour to repreſent this Supreme <hi>Numen</hi> by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62067:23"/>an Image of Gold or Silver, or any other material. To this purpoſe there is a famous paſſage in <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> cited by divers of the Ancient Fathers, where after having aſſerted one only God, the Maker of Heaven and Earth, he condemns all Image-worſhip, and affirms,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe vain Mortals to be deceived and err in their hearts, who graving Images of God out of Stone, Wood, Gold, or Ivory, offer Sacrifices and other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities to them, to the infinite damage of their Souls, and ſuppoſe this to be true Religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>And that the Heathens worſhipped their minor Gods, or inferiour Deities, whether
<hi>Daemons</hi> or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes,</hi> in Images and Statues, is ſo plain and obvious, that it needs no farther proof. Though here the cunning Sophiſters of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to deny the thing it ſelf) have invented many ſhifts and eluſions; and they tell us, that the Pagans worſhipped the dead Images and Statues, and accounted thoſe inanimate and ſenſleſs Figures of Gold, or Silver, or Wood and Stone, to be the very Gods to whom they paid their Religious worſhip.</p>
            <p>But that this is utterly falſe, and made uſe of by the <hi>Bigots</hi> of the Popiſh Church, meerly that their conformity and agreement with the Idolatry of the Heathens might not appear, I ſhall ſhew:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that it is ſuch a piece of ſottiſhneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictious non-ſenſe as is not incident to Humane Nature, that any perſons who are endued with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meaſure and competency of Reaſon and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62067:24"/>ſhould ſo far degenerate and fall from it, as to take Gold, or Silver, or ſome other Material, and frame it into an Image or Statue, and then devoutly court it, and pay the moſt ſolemn Devotion and Religious worſhip to it, by invoking and imploring its aſſiſtance, as hoping to receive great benefits thereby, and yet at the ſame time think it to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a dead and ſenſleſs lump, or piece of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; this, I ſay, is ſo oppoſite to the very Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Principles and Intellectual Furniture of the Soul of Man, that I cannot imagine any number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be guilty of ſuch a perfect piece of ſtupidity. But theſe Images of the Heathens, which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for Religious worſhip, were firſt conſecrated with certain Prayers and Ceremonies, by which they ſuppoſed ſome Inviſible Power ſuperiour to men was conveyed into them, and was ready there to aſſiſt and help all Supplicants to them; ſo that the Image was not worſhipped for it ſelf, as if it were nothing but a dead and lifeleſs Trunk or Stock, but with reſpect to the Demon, or Inviſible Power, which they imagined, after the performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of certain ſacred Ceremonies, was incorporated and dwelt in it. And there is no doubt but that there were many wicked Spirits who induſtriouſly waited to miniſter to the ſins of fond mankind, and did (to uſe the words of <hi>Minutius Felix</hi>) <hi>ſub Statuis &amp; Imaginibus conſecratis deliteſcere,</hi> lurk under the ſhades and covertures of thoſe conſecrated Statues to delude abuſed Mortals.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Heathens conſtantly diſclaimed ſuch a worſhip as this, and tell us, that they knew well enough the value and power of the Image before
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62067:24"/>which they proſtrate themſelves, that it is but a dead and lifeleſs thing in it ſelf, meer Gold, or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or Wood, or Stone, but that they worſhip the Gods in theſe Images. So the Pagans in <hi>Arnobius,</hi> Thou art deceived, and groſly miſtaken; for we [the Heathen] do not believe the ſubſtance of Braſs, <note place="margin">L. 6. <hi>Adv. Gent.</hi>
               </note> or Silver, or Gold, or any other thing of which theſe Statues are made, to be in themſelves Gods; but we worſhip the Gods in theſe. But if nothing will ſerve the turn, but that the Heathens muſt be thought ſuch ſtupid and blockiſh people, as to invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and adore the very Stocks and Stones as Gods, yet have our Adverſaries the Papiſts no ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, if their own <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> be of any credit with them: <hi>To this height of madneſs is it come</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that this piece of Piety little differs from Impiety; for there are a great many of the more rude and ſtupid ſort of people, who worſhip Images of Stone, Wood, Marble, Braſs, or ſuch as are with various colours painted on Walls, not as Figures, but as if thoſe Images had ſome ſenſe in them, and place their truſt and confidence in them, more than in Chriſt, or thoſe Saints to whom they are dedicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having removed this Objection, let us now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to draw the Parallel; which I ſhall do, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the reaſons and grounds the Pagans inſiſted upon, and by which they maintained the worſhip of their Gods in Images and Statues, which were theſe, 1. They declared that in the Adoration of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, the worſhip was not terminated upon the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage as upon the ultimate Object, but directed and referred to the God and his Attributes, whom they adored in and by ſuch an Image; as in the place ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62067:25"/>even now out of <hi>Arnobius.</hi> 2. They affirmed, concerning their Images, that they were Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Repreſentations of the Gods they worſhipped. 3. They uſed Images in their Religious worſhip, as ſenſible helps to excite and quicken their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and fix their Imagination upon. For theſe we have the teſtimony of <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Book <hi>De I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Orig. <hi>contr. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi>
362. where he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the Grave Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers for adoring I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and uſing them as conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols, to raiſe their Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deity.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. No inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate thing ought to be eſteemed for a God, but they who beſtow theſe things upon us, and afford us a continual ſupply thereof for our uſe, have been therefore accounted by us Gods; which Gods are not different to different Nations, as if the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Southern</hi> and the
<hi>Northern</hi> Inhabitants of the Globe, had not any the ſame, but all other different Gods: But as the Sun, and the Moon, and the Heaven, and the Earth, and the Sea, are common to all, though called by ſeveral names in ſeveral Countries; ſo one Reaſon ordering theſe things, and one Providence diſpenſing all, and the inferiour ſubſervient Miniſters thereof having had ſeveral names &amp; honors beſtowed upon them by the Laws of ſeveral Countries, have been every where worſhipped throughout the whole World: And there have been alſo different
<hi>Symbols</hi> conſecrated to them, the better to conduct and lead on mens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings to divine things; though this hath not been without ſome hazard or danger of caſting men upon one or other of theſe two inconveniences, either Superſtition or Atheiſm. From which Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Plutarch</hi> we have theſe things obſervable: 1. That all Nations agreed in the worſhipping of one Supreme and Univerſal <hi>Numen,</hi> Reaſon and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62067:25"/>Providence governing all things. 2. They agreed in worſhipping his ſubſervient Miniſters (the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Providence) appointed by him over all the parts of the World; which being honoured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral Names, and with different Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, according to the Laws of the Reſpective Countries, cauſed all that diverſity of Religions that was amongſt them. 3. That the Pagans did not worſhip the very Images or Statues for Gods, but only as ſymbolical repreſentations of their Gods. 4. That theſe Images or Symbols were to conduct and lead on mens Underſtandings (as ſenſible helps) to Divine things.
5. That Image-worſhip (in the judgment of <hi>Plutarch</hi>) was an In-let and occaſion of Superſtition and Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>Thus far what the Pagans declared concerning their Images; Behold now an admirable and ſweet harmony and conſent between the Image-worſhip of the Heathens, and that now practiſed in the
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church. 1. They likewiſe with the Pagans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the Religious worſhip given to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is not terminated there, but referred to the Prototype, as to its ultimate Object. So the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent,</hi> after having declared that due honour and reverence be given to Images, adds this as one reaſon of it, becauſe the honour exhibited to them, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil.</hi> Trident. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 9.</note> is referred to the Prototypes which they repreſent: ſo that through thoſe Images which we kiſs, and before which we bare our heads, and proſtrate our ſelves, we adore Chriſt, and worſhip the Saints, whoſe ſimilitude they bear; which is ſo like the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology of the Pagan in <hi>Arnobius,</hi> that I think it worth the while to produce it entire; <hi>Sed erras (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62067:26"/>&amp; laberis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Contr. Gentes.</note>
               <hi>nam neque nos aera, neque auri ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentique materias, neque alias quibus ſigna conficiunt, eas eſſe per ſe Deos, &amp; Religioſa decernimus Numina: ſed eos in his colimus, eoſque veneramur quos dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio infert ſacra &amp; fabrilibus efficit inhabitare ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachris; i. e.</hi> Thou art deceived, and groſly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for we [the Heathen] do not believe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Braſs, or Gold, or any other thing of which theſe Statues are made, to be in themſelves Gods; but we worſhip the Gods in theſe, and pay Religious Veneration to thoſe Deities which by Conſecration are brought to inhabit and dwell in thoſe Images or Statues. So that the Pagans argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the ſame manner as the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> or rather that Council giving the ſame reaſon for Image-worſhip with the Pagans, and eſtabliſhing the ſame thing upon the ſame grounds that they did, it muſt needs be guilty of the ſame Crime of Idolatry likewiſe: For if the Heathens in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Images and Statues of their Gods, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the expreſs Sentence of God Almighty, to be heynouſly guilty of Idolatry, though in the mean time they never worſhipped thoſe Images or Statues for themſelves, but in reference to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totypes; it is a clear conſequence, that the Popiſh Image-worſhip, eſtabliſhed upon the ſame grounds and reaſons with the Pagan, will neceſſarily fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame condemnation. To this purpoſe there is a pretty ſtory in an <hi>Italian,</hi> who wrote Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of the Affairs of <hi>India;</hi> When the poor <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians</hi> of
<hi>Nova Hiſpania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pietro Martire</hi> Hiſt. delle Ind. l.
<hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> in the Kingdom of <hi>Mexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> had one day of a ſudden found their Idols taken down and broken, they ſent four Principal Perſons
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62067:26"/>of their Country to <hi>Alfonſus Zuaſus</hi> the Licentiate, who had commanded it: they complaining of the injury, ſuppos'd alſo, and told him, they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be done without his conſent or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as knowing that the Chriſtians had Idols and Images of their own, whom they valued, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and worſhipped; and looking up, and eſpying the Image of S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> whom <hi>Alfonſus</hi> had in great Veneration, hanging by his Bed-ſide, they pointed at him with their finger, ſaying, <hi>The ſame regard which he had to the Image of S.</hi> Sebaſtian, <hi>the ſame they had to theirs.</hi> The Governour being troubled with this quick and not barbarous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, turn'd him about a little, and at laſt told them, <hi>that the Chriſtians did not worſhip Images for their own ſakes, but as they repreſented Holy Perſons dwelling in Heavenly places;</hi> and to demonſtrate that, took down the Image of S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> and broke it in pieces. They reply'd, <hi>that it was juſt ſo with them; and that they were not ſo ſtupid as to worſhip the Images for their own regards, but as they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the Sun, and Moon, and all the Lights of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Alfonſus</hi> being yet more troubled, was forced to ſay, <hi>that the object was different, though the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was not; that the Chriſtians did by their Images paſs honour to the great Creator of the World, but they did it to Creatures, to evil Spirits, and falſe Gods.</hi> But neither in this was there any difference between <hi>Alfonſus</hi> and the poor <hi>Indians,</hi> ſince another Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>Joſephus Acoſta,</hi> affirms of the ſame <hi>Indians,</hi> that they acknowledged the great and Supreme God, and their worſhipping of falſe Gods was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually true of Papiſts; for by giving Religious.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62067:27"/>worſhip to a good Angel, or Saint, that Angel, or Saint, is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> made a falſe God; and being ſo is all one with the Demons of the
<hi>Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Reference to the Prototype, whether it be in Virtue of that Similitude the Images have with thoſe Perſons they repreſent, or whether it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered only as the Image is a Symbolical Preſence at large, it being not regarded whether the Symbol or Image have any Perſonal Similitude with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it repreſents or not, but only as the
<hi>Devotioniſt</hi> takes an occaſion from that to direct his intention to the worſhip of Chriſt, or any Saint; let it be (I ſay) how it will, yet it will no more excuſe a
<hi>Papiſt</hi> than a <hi>Pagan</hi> from Idolatry. For the giving religious worſhip to any Creature, whether to Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or Demons and Heroes, is a making or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving other Gods before the true and everliving God; and this being ſo expreſly forbidden by the God of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> it is moſt certain that all erecting Images to be bowed to, or worſhipped, in reference to theſe, is forbidden alſo. But I am fallen upon the ſecond Branch of the Parallel afore I was aware, that is, that as the Images of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> ſo likewiſe of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> are Symbolical Repreſentations of the Gods they worſhip. That the Image of Chriſt, or of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or of this or that Saint, ſhould be like the carnal Figure of thoſe Perſons while they lived on Earth, is extremely uncertain: ſuppoſe now a devout <hi>Papiſt</hi> bowing down and worſhipping the Image of the Bleſſed Virgin; if this worſhip be given with reſpect to the Perſonal Similitude the Image hath with the Party it repreſents, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall upon ſome other perhaps wicked Perſon,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62067:27"/>and not upon the holy Virgin. The Picture of the beautiful <hi>Curtizan Phryne</hi> was placed upon a high Pillar at <hi>Delphos,</hi> and according to the Features and Lineaments of this, as of the moſt exquiſite Beauty, was drawn the Picture of the Goddeſs
<hi>Venus;</hi> and therefore 'tis certain that the Strumpet <hi>Phryne,</hi> and not the Goddeſs, will be the ultimate object of the religious worſhip given to the ſuppoſed Picture of <hi>Venus:</hi> This (I ſay) will follow upon account of Perſonal Similitude. But that they account them ſymbolical Repreſentations, and worſhip Images as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> worſhipped the Golden Calf with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and intended it as the Symbol of his preſence, is manifeſt from the Images they make of God, wickedly repreſenting the ſacred, and ever-to-be-adored Trinity, under the Figure of an old Man in ſacerdotal Veſtments, with a tripple Crown, and a young Man and a Dove; and this is propoſed not only to be gazed upon, but to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. So <hi>Cajetan;</hi> Images of the Trinity are painted in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 3. <hi>p. Tho.</hi> 9.25. <hi>ar.</hi>
3.</note> not only that they may be ſhewed or looked on, as the Cherubims of old time were in the Temple, but that they may be adored. 3. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> (agreeably to the <hi>Pagans</hi>) affirm, that they uſe Images in their religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as ſenſible helps to excite and ſtir up their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and fix their Imaginations upon. When the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had eſtabliſhed the worſhip of the Images of Chriſt, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and all the Saints, according to the Excellency and Venerabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Prototypes, they add this Reaſon (as <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſays) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For even by theſe are we carried up into a certain Unitive and Conjunctive
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62067:28"/>Viſion, and thereby are vouchſafed that divine and ſupernatural Conjunction, or Contact with the higheſt of all deſirables. As if by the worſhipping of Images the Souls of Men were tranſported beyond themſelves, and carried up in Ecſtatical Raptures to an Union with God himſelf. Which is no more than what Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> who influenced that Council, writes to the Empreſs <hi>Irene</hi> and her Son <hi>Conſtantine; In the whole Chriſtian World</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the holy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are honoured, or worſhipped by Believers; Ut per viſibilem vultum ad inviſibilem Divinitatis Majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mens noſtra ſpirituali affectu rapiatur,</hi> i. e. That by that ſenſible Figure our Mind may be carried by a ſpiritual affection to the inviſible Majeſty of the Divinity. By which Teſtimonies it is clear as the Meridian Light, that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> worſhip Images as helps to quicken and draw up their affections in a more inflamed and vigorous manner to the Deity they adore.</p>
            <p>And though the great Sticklers for Image-worſhip, uſe many Niceties, and raiſe a Cloud of Duſt by their ſubtil Diſtinctions to blind the Eyes of the People, that they may not ſee to the bottom of this their groſs Idolatry, yet can they never clear themſelves from that foul and deteſtable Crime. For though the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> expreſs no particular, but only with great caution define that due honour and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip be given to Images: yet by referring us to the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> it is plain that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> decreed the ſame that the <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil had done before; and the <hi>Nicene</hi> Synod decreed ſuch worſhip to be due to Images, as the Council of <hi>Franefort</hi> ſaid was not due, but condemned by the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62067:28"/>Scriptures and the conſtant Practice of the Primitive Church. To this purpoſe there is a Story in <hi>Roger Hoveden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 1. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. An.
792.</note> a Native Hiſtorian of the Affairs of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: Charles the</hi> French
<hi>King</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſent a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodal into</hi> Britain, <hi>directed unto him from</hi> Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, <hi>in the which Book many things (out alas) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, and repugnant to right Faith, were found; eſpecially it was confirmed almoſt by the unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all the</hi> Eaſtern <hi>Doctors, no leſs than three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or more, That Images ought to be worſhipped; which thing the Church of God doth altogether deteſt and abhor.</hi> Againſt which Synodal Book <hi>Albinus</hi> wrote an Epiſtle marvellouſly confirmed by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Divine Scripture, and carried the ſame to the <hi>French</hi> King, together with the foreſaid Book, in the name of our Biſhops and Princes. And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Britain,</hi> but in other places, this abominable Practice of Image-worſhip was condemned by the beſt and wiſeſt Men, of the beſt times and ages. The Council of <hi>Eliberis</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> forbad the uſe of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in Churches, for this reaſon, <note place="margin">Eliber. Can. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Leſt that which is worſhipped, or adored, be painted upon the Walls.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe the fourth Council at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> cites the ſame words of
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> againſt placing Images in Churches. Thus another Synod at
<hi>Conſtantinople</hi> conſiſting of 338 Biſhops under <hi>Conſtantius Copronymus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. Dom. 753.</note> forbad all religious uſe of Images, in Churches, or out of them. And ſo much of their Decree as prohibited the worſhip of Images, was again confirm'd by the Council of <hi>Francfort,</hi> where the Biſhops of <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> were aſſembled by the command of the Emperour
<hi>Charles</hi> the Great, to that purpoſe. To
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62067:29"/>theſe we may add the Council of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and the ſecond Council of
<hi>Sens,</hi> in which Image-worſhip was oppoſed and cautioned againſt. And a <hi>Greek</hi> Hiſtorian informs us, that when <hi>Frederick</hi> 1. the Emperour, who led his Army to the Conqueſt of the <hi>Holy Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Njcetas Chron. <hi>l. 2.</hi> An. Dom.
<hi>1180.</hi>
               </note> entered into <hi>Armenia,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of thoſe Parts did lovingly receive them, becauſe the worſhip of Images was not admitted amongſt them, as amongſt other <hi>Northern</hi> People. And laſtly, for the Doctrine and Practice of the firſt and beſt ages of the Church, it was very remarkable what is told by <hi>Aelius Lampridius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Alexander Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> That when <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Churches to be built without Images, it was ſuppoſed he intended them for the ſervice of Chriſt: <hi>Than which</hi> (ſaith that learned Biſhop Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>)
<hi>there needs no greater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ductor dubit. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi>
2.</note> 
               <hi>or clearer Inſtance of the Doctrine and Practice of the holy</hi> Primitives.</p>
            <p>But I had almoſt forgotten the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Images, which runs exactly Parallel with that of the <hi>Heathens.</hi> Of the <hi>Pagans</hi> it is reported that they conſecrated the Statues and Images of their Gods with certain Prayers and Ceremonies, (before they paid any Religious Veneration to them,) by vertue whereof they ſuppoſed ſome extraordinary Powers, or Vertues, were acquired and reſided in them. <note place="margin">Vid. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut. Fel.</note> Such were all thoſe Teleſmatical Images which were conſecrated to certain purpoſes, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtop the rage and fury of Fire, or ſudden Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations; or to hinder the ſudden Incurſions of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: To which laſt purpoſe I remember Mr.
<hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> cites a Story of certain Teleſmatical Statues, or Images, hid in the Ground upon the Borders of <hi>Thrace,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:62067:29"/>which when upon ſome occaſion they were digged up, the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſoon after over ran the whole Country. Of this nature was the <hi>Trojan Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and thoſe Images of the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> in which they repoſed ſuch confidence, that they derided <hi>David,</hi> as thinking that ſo long as thoſe conſecrated Statues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the City, it was impoſſible it ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: <hi>Except thou take away the blind and the lame, thou ſhalt not come in hither; thinking</hi> David <hi>cannot come in hither.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.6.</note> The wit of Man certainly cannot find any difference between the Conſecration of thoſe Images of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and the Dedication of the Golden, or Wooden Images of the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> For thus runs the Prayer at the Conſecration of the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary, Sanctifie, O God, this Image of the Bleſſed Virgin, that it may bring ſaving help to thy faithful People, that Thunders and Lightnings may be driven away the ſooner; that immoderate Rains, or Floods, and Civil wars, or the Invaſion of</hi> Heathens
<hi>may at the Preſence of this be ſuppreſſed.</hi> In a word, it is very plain from their publick and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized Practice, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> conſecrrate their Images, they hope in them, they expect Gifts and Graces from them, they Clothe them and Crown them, they erect Altars and Temples to them, they kiſs them and bow the Head and Knee before them, they light up Tapers and Lamps to them, which is a direct conſumptive Sacrifice; and (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſays of the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Hereticks, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> who had gotten the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or Pictures of Chriſt, <hi>Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and other Philoſophers,) <hi>Reliquam obſervationem circa eas ſimiliter ut gentes faciunt,</hi> they do to their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as the <hi>Heathens</hi> do to theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62067:30"/> I know nothing now that can by any Papiſt be brought, with any ſhew of reaſon, to invalidate what I have here ſaid, unleſs it be that common ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge, that they are indeed forbidden to make or worſhip the Image of any falſe God, but that they are not interdicted the worſhipping of the true God, or his Saints, in Images and Statues. The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and foolery of which Plea, though it have been already demonſtrated by divers learned Perſons, yet I ſhall here reply ſomething to it, partly to gratifie the ſincere and unprejudiced Reader, and withal, to render my Diſcourſe upon this Point more unexcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable and entire.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I ſay, that the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Decalogue forbids both the making of an Image to the true God, and likewiſe the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, in reference to Saints and Angels. And whereas the Papiſts do grant, that the Precept binds ſtrongly as to the Prohibition of the worſhip of the Images of falſe Gods, I ſhall take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this their Conceſſion, and make uſe of it to overthrow, even out of their own mouths, their Doctrine of worſhipping Images, in reference to Saints and Angels. Thus therefore I argue; There is no more than one God, and the reſt no otherwiſe made Gods, than by giving Religious worſhip to them; of which erecting conſecrated Images to them, and bowing to them, is one Mode: And therefore theſe Saints and Angels to whom Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip is given by a Law, do
<hi>ipſo facto</hi> become Gods, but not true Gods, but falſe Gods; and therefore the worſhipping of their Images is ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbidden in this ſecond Commandment, by the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62067:30"/>full confeſſion of Papiſts themſelves, who ſay the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of falſe Gods are here prohibited.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay, that the True and Ever-living God hath ſo ſtrictly forbidden the worſhipping of himſelf by any Image whatever, that repreſents any thing within the comprehenſion of the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> worſhipped the
<hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf</hi> (which was intended for a ſymbolical re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the true God) they ſo far provoked his wrath by this their heynous Crime of Idolatry, that notwithſtanding there fell thouſands of them by the Sword, yet God threatens to remember that very tranſgreſſion upon them in future Ages: ſo that it is commonly ſaid by the <hi>Jews,</hi> that in every Plague and Captivity that fell upon them, there was an Ounce of the <hi>Calf,</hi> God continuing to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh this ſin in all their Poſterities, that continued to provoke him with the like.</p>
            <p>Now that this <hi>Golden Calf</hi> was not the Image of a falſe God, as ſuppoſe the
<hi>Egyptian Oſiris,</hi> or ſome other particular and inferiour Deity, but deſigned for the ſymbolical preſence of the true and ever-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, appears from the whole Hiſtory of it, in which there are ſo many pregnant proofs, that this <hi>Cherub</hi> or <hi>Calf</hi> was intended for a Symbol of the preſence of the true God, that none but a humour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and prejudiced mind can underſtand it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. 1. The firſt thing that offers it ſelf is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this Idolatry, which aroſe from the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Moſes;</hi> for he ſtaying in the Mount for forty days, they took it for granted they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear any more tidings of him; ſo we read, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>And when the people ſaw that</hi> Moſes
<hi>delayed to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62067:31"/>come down out of the Mount, the people gathered themſelves together unto</hi> Aaron, <hi>and ſaid unto him, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p, make us Gods which ſhall go before us; for as for this</hi> Moſes, <hi>the man that brought us up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>we wot not what is become of him.</hi> Here we plainly ſee, that when after many days ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> they heard no tidings of him, they ſollicit <hi>Aaron</hi> to make them Gods to go before them, that is, to bring them onward to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Land, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had hitherto done. 2. When the people had thus wrought on the timorous nature of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and he, according to their deſire, had fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Golden Cherub</hi> of the Ear-rings they brought him, they no ſooner ſaw it, but they cry out, <hi>Theſe be thy Gods,</hi> O Iſrael,
<hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt; or, as 'tis related in <hi>Nehem.</hi>
9.18. <hi>This is thy God that brought thee up out of</hi> Egypt. Now let any man but of an ordinary underſtanding conſider, whether if this Molten Image were the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of a falſe God, as ſuppoſe the <hi>Egyptian Iſis, Serupis,</hi> or <hi>Oſinis,</hi> the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> could be ſo weak and ſottiſh as to ſay of it, that that was it which brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> eſpecially when the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution done upon all the Tutelar Deities of <hi>Egypt</hi> was yet freſh in their minds, who were notable to ſave themſelves, or protect their charge, when God deſtroyed all the Firſt-born in the Land. 3. The people of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> acknowledge that the <hi>Cherub</hi> or <hi>Calf</hi> that <hi>Aaron</hi> made, was the ſymbolical preſence of that God that brought them out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> now they never thought that it was either <hi>Serapis,</hi> or <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiris,</hi> or any other <hi>Egyptian</hi> Deity, that brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but the true God, the Creator of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62067:31"/>Heaven and Earth, whoſe preſence they lately ſaw in ſuch terrible Majeſty upon Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> 4. When <hi>Aaron</hi> had finiſhed the matter of their ſin, he makes a Proclamation throughout the Camp, <hi>To morrow is a Feaſt of the Lord, v.</hi>
5. not to the Idol, or falſe God, but to <hi>Jehovah</hi> the true God; whereas if this
<hi>Golden Calf</hi> had been the ſymbol of ſome <hi>Egyptian</hi> God, and the people had fallen into Paganiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, it had been very improper for <hi>Aaron</hi> to have proclaimed this his Sacrifice a Feaſt to the Lord. 5. Neither here nor afterwards, when <hi>Aaron</hi> relates the whole proceeding to <hi>Moſes</hi> when he came down from the Mount, is there any mention of any thing that may give the leaſt ſuſpition or intimation that this graven Image was the ſymbol or repreſentation of a falſe God, but much to evince the contrary; foraſmuch as here is no name of any particular falſe God (which yet is uſual in Scripture, when in other places it relates their lapſe into Polytheiſm and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry) but a Solemn Feaſt proclaimed to the Lord <hi>Jehovah:</hi> And although this <hi>Calf</hi> was only intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them to be a Symbol of the preſence of the true God, yet being directly contrary to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and having Divine Worſhip given to it, it became a perfect piece of groſs and ſoul Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance of the like nature we have in the Idolatry practiſed by <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> for that the Calves which he placed in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and built Altars, and ſacrificed to them, were Hieroglyphicks or ſymbolical repreſentations of the true God, and not the Images of falſe Gods, is plain and evident. 1. In that there is no mention of
<hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Gods of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or any other adjoyning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſh
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62067:32"/>Nation; whereas when <hi>Solomon</hi> in his old Age was drawn away by his Wives to commit Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, there is a particular account and enumeration of the falſe Gods he adored, as <hi>Aſhtoreth</hi> the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs of the <hi>Zidonians, Chemoſh</hi> the God of the
<hi>Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> and <hi>Milcom</hi> the God of the Children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> but of
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> it is only ſaid, that he made two Calves of Gold, and ſaid to the people,
<hi>It is too much for you to go up to</hi> Jeruſalem: <note place="margin">1 Kin. 12.28,
29.</note> 
               <hi>Behold thy Gods,</hi> O Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt: <hi>And he ſet the one in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in</hi> Dan. 2. The ſin of
<hi>Ahab,</hi> which was the Introduction of Polytheiſm, and the height of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Idolatry, (and therefore is ſignally called in Scripture, <hi>the way of</hi> Ahab) is accounted greater in Gods ſight than the ſin of <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> which is a plain ſign, that the way of
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> was not the worſhipping falſe Gods (for that is called the way of the Houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi>) but the worſhipping the true God in an Image. Thus it is written of
<hi>Jehoram</hi> the Son of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 Kings 3.2, 3. <hi>And he wrought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in the ſight of the Lord, but not like his Father, and like his Mother; for he put away the Image of</hi> Baal
<hi>that his Father had made: Nevertheleſs he cleaved unto the ſins of</hi> Jeroboam <hi>the Son of</hi> Nebat, <hi>which made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſin, he departed not therefrom.</hi> 3. In that the object of his Idolatry was a <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> it ſeems to be the very ſame prevarication that <hi>Aaron</hi> was led into by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſoon after the delivery of the Law or ten Commandments upon Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi> and that theſe Calves, as well as that made by <hi>Aaron,</hi> were deſigned for ſymbols of the preſence of the true God; and that being a violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62067:32"/>of the expreſs Command of God, and ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by him in the ſevere puniſhment of the ſin, ſo likewiſe were theſe, and both alike Idolatry. 4. The ſame form of words is uſed by <hi>Jeroboam</hi> at the Dedication of theſe Calves, that was afore-time made uſe of by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when <hi>Aaron</hi> made the Molten Calf:
<hi>Theſe be thy Gods, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt. Now they knew, and never thought otherwiſe, that it was neither <hi>Chemoſh,</hi> nor
<hi>Milcom,</hi> nor <hi>Aſhtoreth,</hi> nor <hi>Dagon,</hi> nor any other Pagan Deity, but the true God who delivered them from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage. 5. <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> continues the ſame Feaſts and way of worſhip which were at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and therefore 'tis moſt likely, he deſigned ſtill the worſhip of the true God in theſe Calves, which were ſet up as ſymbols of his preſence. 6. It was not agreeable to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical end or reaſon which
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> propounded to himſelf, to eſtabliſh that part of Pagan Idolatry which conſiſted in Polytheiſm; for his only aim was, to hinder the people, by this Project, from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to do Sacrifice in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> leſt by that they ſhould be tempted to return to the obedience of their natural Prince: for thus he expreſſes his own fears,
<hi>And</hi> Jeroboam <hi>ſaid in his heart, now ſhall the Kingdom return to the Houſe of</hi> David: <note place="margin">1 Kin. 12.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>If this people go up to do Sacrifice in the Houſe of the Lord at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>then ſhall the heart of this people turn again unto their Lord, even unto</hi> Rehoboam <hi>King of</hi> Judah; <hi>and they ſhall kill me, and go again to</hi> Rehoboam <hi>King of</hi> Judah. Now if this worſhip which he eſtabliſhed had been the worſhip of ſtrange and forreign Gods, it would no ways have comported with his end, which was to aſſure the ten Tribes to himſelf. 7. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62067:33"/>only argues againſt the place, and not any thing againſt the way or manner of worſhip per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> for he only tells them, it was too much for them to go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but if they would hearken to him, they might worſhip God as well in another place as there, for he placed an Image at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and another at
<hi>Dan,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſymbols or viſible repreſentations of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the true God that brought them out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> they might ſacrifice and perform their other Divine Rites and Ceremonies to them, and not trouble themſelves any further. 8. To which may be added, in the laſt place, that it is the moſt unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and improbable thing in the World, that
<hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> at his very firſt entrance upon the Kingdom, ſhould eſtabliſh the very ſame Idolatry for which the Kingdom was rent from the houſe of <hi>Solomon;</hi> for when the Prophet <hi>Ahijah</hi> tells <hi>Jereboam</hi> that the Lord would rend the Kingdom out of the hand of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and give ten Tribes to him, and make him King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the reaſon is given, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.33. <hi>Becauſe they had forſaken God, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped</hi> Aſhtoreth <hi>the Goddeſs of the</hi> Zidonians, Chemoſh <hi>the God of the</hi> Meabites, <hi>and</hi> Milcom <hi>the God of the Children of</hi> Ammon. And therefore it is very childiſh and ridion lous to imagine, that <hi>Jeruboram</hi> would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce that very Idolatry at his firſt coming, for the practice of which God had threatned to pull the Kingdom out of the hand of his Maſter. Theſe two Examples do ſufficiently and fully inſtruct us in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe and meaning of God in the ſecond Commandment, that he forbid all worſhip of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by an Image, and that the making of deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62067:33"/>any ſuch Image, though for his honour, is pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and groſs Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I might now likewiſe, for a concluſion of this Argument, bring another inſtance of the groſſeſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry that ever was committed by men, ſolemnly practiſed by the
<hi>Romiſts</hi> Church, and injoyned by their Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and that is, their worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Bread in the Sacrament, which they can the Adoration of the Hoſt, than which (beſides the Idolatry involved in it) I cannot find any Rite or Cuſtom ſo barbarous in the whole Pagan Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſs I ſhould bring in the <hi>Cannibals</hi> or
<hi>Man-Eaters:</hi> And if the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> prove falſe (as there is nothing more certain) then by the teſtimony of <hi>Coſterus</hi> the Jeſuit, there never was the like piece of Idolatry practis'd in the World before: Take his own words:
<note place="margin">Enchirid. Contr. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For the errours of thoſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were more tolerable, who worſhip ſome Golden or Silver Statue, or ſome Image of any other Materials for their God, as the Heathen worſhipped their Gods; or a Red Cloth hung upon the top of a Spear, as is reported of the</hi> Laplanders, <hi>or ſome live-Animal, as of old the</hi> Egyptians <hi>did, than of theſe that worſhip a bit of Bread, as hitherto the Chriſtians have done all over the world for ſo many hundred years, if the Doctrine of</hi> Tranſubſtantion <hi>be not true,</hi> From this Teſtimony then we are informed, that if
<hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> be a Fiction, then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is guilty of Idolatry, and ſo groſs a piece of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, as a man can find no inſtance in Paganiſm to liken it to. And that the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> is a ridiculous Figment, a thing without Senſe or Reaſon impoſed upon the World, I refer to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62067:34"/>thoſe learned Authors who have on purpoſe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the falſity of it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I have ſhown that Almighty God by ſending his Son, our Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, into the World, deſigned the replantation of his own bleſſed Nature and Image in mens Souls: And that this might be the more fully and effectually accompliſhed, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined likewiſe to root out and extirpate all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, which both debaſed the Majeſty of the Great God, and rendred mens Minds low, contemptible, and abject: and having in the general diſcovered ſome of thoſe Doctrines averred and maintained in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which directly overthrow this great Purpoſe of making men Partakers of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Godlike Spirit; I ſhall now produce ſome other inſtances, and ſhew how the practice of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church deſtroys thoſe other two branches of the Divine Life, that is, Purity or Holineſs, and Love and Charity.</p>
            <p>And for the firſt of theſe, that is, Purity and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, it is wholly evacuated by ſuch Doctrines and Practices as miniſter to the Vices of men, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile Heaven and Salvation with the moſt licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious courſes of ſin and wickedneſs, ſuch as ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate all the Arguments uſed in the Goſpel to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a ſtrict and holy Converſation, and are apt to give allowance and incouragement to a wicked life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To this end and purpoſe the Doctrine of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory is hugely ſubſervient; which beſides that it is a Politick Device to ſqueeze and drain mens Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from them, and ſo inrich the Clergy, though with the Damnation of the Laity, it is likewiſe fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62067:34"/>for the cheriſhing and pampering mens carnal luſts and affections, and gives them hope of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation upon no difficult terms, though they have not been ſo careful in providing for it in this life-time, as Chriſt in his holy Goſpel has commanded and injoyned them to be. For ſince the worſt of men amongſt Chriſtians (if they take any care, and uſe any competent circumſpection) may be diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from theſe Earthly Regions with fair hopes and aſſurances, (if not of going directly to Heaven) yet at leaſt of an entrance into Purgatory (where-ever it be, whether in a Torrid or Frozen Zone) it muſt needs be a wonderful gratification to their Animal Faculties, and Senſitive Lives, to indulge and pleaſe them to the full, and yet eſcape the torments of Hell at the laſt. We have ſeen that if a wicked man live and die without the practice of Chriſtian Virtues, and with the habits of many damnable ſins unmortified, yet if at the laſt moment and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his life, he have but an act of Attrition, and confeſs to his Ghoſtly Father, (who is bound upon this to abſolve him) he ſhall certainly be ſaved; which is incouragement enough to vicious perſons to go on in ſin, and venture the odds of a ſurprize, or ſudden death, upon ſuch eaſie terms: But if a man be ſo careleſs and wretchedly ſtupid, as not to mind the making ſatisfaction for mortal ſins in this life, ſo long as he is aſſured by an Infallible Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood it may be done in the next, the worſt that can happen to him between Death and Judgment, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſtate of Purgatory; that is, he muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſome ſtrange torment, God knows where, in Fire, or Hail, or Snow, or Ice. And this truly is a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62067:35"/>ſad &amp; uncomfortable condition, but ſtill there is ſome hope left, &amp; the redemption from this Diſmal Priſon prevents all deſpair of lying for ever under this ſevere Reſtraint. Therefore this good natur'd Church of <hi>Rome</hi> bids them take heart, and tells them that there is an Expiation of Sin after Death by the Prayers of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> That the Souls in Purgatory are delivered thence <hi>fidelium ſuffragiis, potiſſimum vero acceptal ili Altaris ſaorificio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſſ. 25.</note> i. e. by the Suffrages of the faithful, but eſpecially by the acceptable Sacrifice of the Altar. And giving Directions to Biſhops, the Council ſays, <hi>Let Biſhops take care that the Suffrages of the faithful now living,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Sacrifices of Maſſes, Prayers, Almſ-deeds, and other Works of Piety, which according to the Conſtitution of the Church ought to be performed for the faithful deceaſed, that they be done piouſly and devoutly,</hi> &amp;c. And they Anathematize every one that ſhall ſay, <hi>The Sacrifice of the Maſs is a waked Commemoration of that Sacrifice on the Croſs, and not Propitiatory: or that it only profits him that receives it, and ought not to be offered for the Living and the Dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſſ. 22. Can. 3.</note> 
               <hi>for Sins, Puniſhments, Satisfactions, and other Neceſſities.</hi> There is no great danger then that a Man ſhould lye long in Purgatory, if he have either Mony or Friends, for either of theſe ways a Man may eſcape.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt of the Indulgences conferr'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Con-fraternity of the
<hi>Roſary</hi> this is one, That every time they recite the whole <hi>Roſary</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, they gain the delivery of a Soul out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. And though Charity grow cold, and there be little to be done for Love, yet Money that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62067:35"/>all things, will open the Gates of Purgatory, and deliver whoever the Donor pleaſes: <note place="margin">De Miſſ. l. 3. c. 10.</note> for ſome Monks have taught, (as the learned. <hi>Mornay</hi> relates,) that the Souls which are in Purgatory do leap at the ſound of the Money when it is caſt into the Baſon for them; ſo comfortable a thing is Gold. The poor Sinner indeed is in the worſt condition, who has few Friends and leſs Money; and truly for ought I can ſee ſuch a one living obſcurely may dye without much regard or concern, and being quickly forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten may ly the whole time in Purgatory, which is not ten years ſay <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Zeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> But for thoſe who are of Ability to purchaſe Maſſes and Sacrifices, by leaving round ſums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney at their Death, they need not fear the ſtaying ſo much as a day in Purgatory: So that it need not be ſaid, <hi>How hard,</hi> but how eaſie,
<hi>is it for a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this excellent Doctrine, and very well fitted for the encouragement of a wicked Life?
<hi>Skin for Skin; and all that a Man hath will he give for his Life;</hi> and he were a very Foor that would not part with ſome of his Eſtate to be freed from the puniſhment of his ſins, and be made happy for ever. But alas our Miniſters cannot give us ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent encouragements as theſe, nor can they with ſafe Conſciences tell us that Money will open the Gates of <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> but they tell us in ſober ſadneſs that if we live bad Lives, we ſhall certainly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably be miſerable. They have no ways of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men from Hell and Damnation, but only by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them in their Life time to be truly penitent and ſincere; nor will they promiſe and ſecure any
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62067:36"/>that their ſins are pardoned upon any other terms than that godly ſorrow that works repentance never to be repented of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if this Proviſion be too narrow, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a Courſe of Debauchery and Licentiouſneſs, his Holineſs, like a moſt kind and indulgent Father, will give his Children no cauſe of complaint; but as well out of a prudent regard to his own Coffers, as an earneſt deſire to give his Sons as ample a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to follow all the extravagant and enormous moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Fleſh and Blood as Heart can wiſh, he grants many Indulgences and Diſpenſations for ſin and wickedneſs. And though we ſqueamiſh and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Proteſtants who check at every Sin, may think ſtrange that Chriſt's Vicar (as he calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) ſhould act ſo contrary to the Intereſt of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Lord; yet the Plenitude of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power will warrant this, and much more. <hi>For his Power</hi> (as <hi>Du Ranchin,</hi> who was no Proteſtant, ſpeaks) <hi>hath neither Banks nor Bottom; and his Juriſdiction ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends over all the World, even as low as Hell and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and as high as Heaven, taking hold of great and ſmall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Review of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent,</hi> l. 2. c. 10.</note>
               <hi>Clerks and Laicks, things ſacred and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane:</hi> And afterwards he gives divers Inſtances of the fulneſs of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power out of their own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>viz. That the</hi> Pope <hi>is a God upon Earth, that God and he have one and the ſame Conſiſtory; that he can go againſt all Councils and Statutes; that he can make wrong to be right: To whom no Man may ſay, Why do you ſo? Whoſe Power may not be diſputed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out incurring the Crime of Sacriledge, foraſmuch as he is the Cauſe of Cauſes, and the juſt Cauſe; and for that it it is to be preſumed that whatſoever pleaſes him is juſt and reaſonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:62067:36"/> Now he that hath but Faith enough to believe thoſe vaſt Prorogatives of his Holineſs, need never queſtion the Validity of his Indulgences and Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations for Sin. And that we may not think this unlimited Power to be only the fawning of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites and Court-flatterers, <hi>Clement</hi> the VI. in his <hi>Bull</hi> of altering the <hi>Jubilee</hi> gives us a Specimen of it, where among other things he ordains, <hi>That if a Man be going to</hi> Rome <hi>upon Devotion, in the year of</hi> Jubilee, <hi>and happen to dye by the way, he ſhall be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally acquitted and abſolved of all his ſins.</hi> And he afterwards adds,
<hi>Howſoever we command the Angels of</hi> Paradiſe, <hi>that they convey his Soul into the glory of</hi> Paradiſe, <hi>being totally abſolved from the pains of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</hi> Well ſpoken brave Head of this Church! we will truſt thee for finding out an eaſie way to Heaven at any time.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Rome</hi> there are ſo many Churches, Altars, and Croſſes that have ſuch an inexhauſtible ſtock of Indulgences granted to them by ſeveral <hi>Popes,</hi> that a Man cannot miſs a full Remiſſion and Pardon of all his ſins.</p>
            <p>And that we may not think our holy Father the <hi>Pope</hi> has forgotten his Children in
<hi>England,</hi> or any other place far diſtant from <hi>Rome,</hi> he has provided Pardon and Salvation for theſe at as eaſie a Rate as can be deſired; By Grant from <hi>Pope John</hi> the XX. every bowing of the Head at the naming of <hi>Jeſus</hi> gets twenty years pardon: And to grace the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony the more, Sir <hi>Edwin. Sands</hi> ſays, <note place="margin">Europae ſpec.</note> he has heard ſundry of their famous Divines teach in the Pulpit, <hi>That Chriſt himſelf on the Croſs bowed his Head on the right ſide, to reverence his own Name that was written over it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:62067:37"/> Again, <hi>The ſaying of the Beads over with a Medal, or other Trinket of the</hi> Pope<hi>'s Benediction appendant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gets a Plenary Indulgence; and delivers what Soul out of Purgatory one pleaſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now one would imagine that his Holineſs had given ample ſatisfaction to all his dearly belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Children; but becauſe ſome are apt to be queru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and complaining, out of his abundant Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he has been pleaſed to rate and ſet a Price upon moſt Sins, that they may know before they act any Villany what an Abſolution will coſt: The Book is called <hi>Taxa Cancellariae Apoſtolice, The Tax of the Apoſtolical Chancery,</hi> and was ſet forth by Pope
<hi>Leo</hi> the X. Of which Book in the firſt place hear <hi>Du Ranchin</hi>'s cenſure,
<note place="margin">Review of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent,</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> who ſpeaking of the diſhoneſt Arts and Tricks the Popes uſe to get Money, refers thoſe that deſire further Information, to a Book In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>Taxa Cancellaria Apoſtolica,</hi> Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> 1520. <hi>And yet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>this is nothing in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the Penitentiary Tax printed with the ſame Book, where every Sin, every Crime, how heynous ſoever, hath his Price ſet; ſo that to have a Licenſe and Impunity for ſinning, there needs no more than to be rich; to have a Paſport to</hi> Paradiſe, <hi>both for himſelf and his miſdeeds.</hi> But (that which might make <hi>Rome</hi> bluſh, if there were any ſhame in her Brow) theſe Pardons and Indulgences are denyed to the Poor and Indigent, who are not of Means ſufficient, to raiſe theſe Criminal and Inceſtuous Impoſitions. So that we live not in thoſe days when it was harder for a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than for a Camel to go through the Eye of a Needle; for now the Kingdom of Heaven belongs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62067:37"/>to them, and not to thoſe beggarly Creatures that have nothing but a Staff and a Wallet.</p>
            <p>Take likewiſe the Complaint of <hi>Claudius Eſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus,</hi> a famous Doctor of
<hi>Sorbon,</hi> cited by the ſame Author: <note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Ep. ad. Tit.</note>
               <hi>There is a Book publickly ſet to every Mans view</hi> (ſays he) <hi>which ſells as well now as ever, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled</hi> Taxa Cancellariae Apoſtolicae, <hi>which is proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ſet out for gain, like a common whore, whence more naughtineſs is learned than from all the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists, and Summaries of all Vices.</hi> There is Licenſe granted for many of them, and Abſolution for all; but only to ſuch as will buy them. I forbear the names, <hi>For</hi> (as one ſays) <hi>they are very fearful, even the ſound of them.</hi> It is ſtrange that in theſe times, in this Sohiſm, that Index and Inventory of ſo many unclean and abominable Villanies, ſo Infamous that I am confident there is not a more ſcandalous Book in all
<hi>Germany, Switzerland,</hi> or any other place which hath ſeparated from the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> was not ſuppreſſed: Yea, it is ſo far from being ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Treaſurers of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Licenſes and Impunities for thoſe ſo many, and ſuch horrible Crimes, are renewed; and for the moſt part confirmed by the Faculties of the Legats, which come from thence into theſe Quarters, with Power to reſtore to their former Eſtate all things that were utterly loſt; and ſo to legitimate all Baſtards, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſuch as were begot by any unlawful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction; to allow People Marriage with ſuch as they had formerly committed Adultery with, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſuch as were perjured, Simoniacal, Falſifiers, Robbers, Uſurers, Schiſmaticks, Hereticks recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yea, and even to admit them to Orders, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62067:38"/>Dignities, and all ſorts of Benefices; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with caſual, not wilful Murderers, howbeit the fore-cited Tax doth not except wilful Parricides, Killers of Father, Mother, Brother, Siſter, Children, or Wife; Sorcerers, Enchanters, Concubine-keepers, Adulterers, Inceſtuous with Parents or Kindred, <hi>Sodomites,</hi> Sinners againſt Nature, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of themſelves with Beaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O that <hi>Rome</hi> would from henceforth have ſome ſhame, and ceaſe to ſet out ſuch a ſhameleſs Catalogue of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wickedneſs. This Paſſage is warily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be blotted out in their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Index.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Peter de Moulin</hi> ſaith, <hi>That this Book was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed at</hi> Paris
<hi>by</hi> Toſſanus Dionyſius <hi>in S.</hi> James<hi>'s Street,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. Temp. Pont. Rom.</note> 
               <hi>at the wooden Croſs, the King's Priviledge, and the Pope's Bull being annexed to it.</hi> And the Lord <hi>Morney</hi> ſpeaking of theſe Books, faith,
<hi>They are no leſs commonly uſed among the Pope's Brokers, than Calendars with Husbandmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Myſtr. Iniq.</note> 
               <hi>or the Book of Cuſtoms and Entries among Merchants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Sink of wickedneſs; which I have here diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, cannot but be extremely offenſive to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſenſes of every true Chriſtian, therefore I ſhall haſten as faſt as I can from it, only citing a Paſſage out of <hi>Dr. Ranchin,</hi> with a pleaſant Story relating to it. <note place="margin">Review of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent.</hi> l. 5. c. 1.</note>
               <hi>It is ordinary</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with the Popes to grant a plenary Pardon of all Sins, with this Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, [Be they never ſo he ynous,] not only at the great</hi> Jubilee, <hi>but alſo in particular Bulls:</hi> And he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in that of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the V.
<hi>An.</hi> 1588. grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Catholicks of <hi>France. But that</hi> (ſays he) <hi>which is yet more to be condemned in them, is, that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62067:38"/>the Popes de not only give remiſſion of ſins already committed, but alſo of ſuch as are to be committed, which is a means to obligex all the haſt Raſcals in the World unto him, and to give them occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double their Crimes and Miſdemeanours; to rob with four hands, to kill Father and Mother, to ſet upon their Lords and Maſters, to violate the Authority of their Princes, and uſurp their Dominions: For pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they can make their Party ſtronger, and that they be devout towards the H. See, there will be no want of an Indulgence; yea even without that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways provided they pay their</hi> Rent.</p>
            <p>The ſtory is this:
<q>In the time of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, <hi>Tetzelius,</hi> a Fryar, was ſent into
<hi>Germany</hi> with a great number of Pardoris to advance Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for his Holineſs: This Factor highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Wares where ever he came, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that he could pardon all ſins, both paſt, and to come: whereupon a <hi>German</hi> Gentleman bought ſuch a one of him, and afterwards rob'd the Pardoner: <hi>Tetzelius</hi> was highly offended, and threatned him with Bell, Book, and Candie: But the Gentleman anſwered, <hi>That he had bought his Pardon for it;</hi> declaring, <hi>that was the Sin he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to commit, when he made that Purchaſe.</hi>
               </q> To which the poor Fryar knew not what to reply.</p>
            <p n="1">10. The laſt great end and purpoſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of our Lord Jeſus was (as I have ſhown) to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and propagate an Univerſal Love and Charity: but how far removed from this excellent temper and ſpirit the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is, their practice is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient witneſs: For he that ſhall conſider how they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62067:39"/>brand us of the Reformation with the odious name of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and how impiouſly diligent they have been to exadicate and extirpate the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion out of the world, perſecuting it in all places where their Power extends with all imaginable cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty; and withal remembers, that (as the often-cited Author tells us) it is a Maxim of the Jeſuits,
<hi>That if any manexamine the Doctrine of the Pope by the Rule of Gods Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Du Rau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeing that it is different, chance to contradict it, let him be rooted out with Fire and Sword:</hi> He, I ſay, that deeply reflects upon theſe things, will find that Inſtruments of Cruelty are in their Habitations, and that their tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are like thoſe of the wicked. Our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour once rebuked the indiſcreet zeal of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, when they would have called for Fire from Heaven to conſume the ungrateful <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and tells them, <hi>that he came not to deſtroy mend liver, but to ſave them:</hi> But the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, as if ſhe had owned no other Lord but him who was a Murderer from the beginning, thinks it not enough to call for Fire from Heaven, but ſearches Earth and Hell too to deſtroy harmleſs and innocent perſons. <hi>The good Shepherd</hi> (ſaid the meek Lamb of God) <hi>lays down his life for his ſheep:</hi> But the proud and bloody Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with his Idolatrous Clergy, are ſo far from this Divine Spirit, that they drive them to the Shambles, and out their throats without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe; witneſs thoſe many barbarous Maſſacres and Butcheries of men, for no other reaſon, but becauſe they could not bow the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> and joyn with an Idolatrous Church againſt the expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62067:39"/>of the Living God. The barbarous Murders of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> and
<hi>Waldenſes</hi> remain a laſting Monument of unparallell'd Popiſh Cruelty; of whom
<hi>Reinerius,</hi> an Inquiſitor of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> thus writes; <note place="margin">Contr. Haret. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Among all the Sects which have formerly been, none is more pernicious to the Church, than that of the</hi> Leoniſts; <hi>and that for theſe three Reaſons.</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe it is of longer continuance than any other, for ſame ſay it hath laſted ever ſince Pope</hi> Sylveſter, <hi>others ſay ever ſince the Apoſtles.</hi> 2. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Sect is more general than this, for there is ſcarce any Country in which it is not found.</hi> 3. <hi>That whereas other Sects deter and affright men with the horridneſs of their blaſphemies againſt God, this Sect of the</hi> Leoniſts <hi>makes a great ſhew of godlineſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they live righteouſly before men, and believe all things rightly touching God, and concerning all other Articles of the Creed, only they ſpeak evil of the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Church and Clergy, in which thing the Laity is very forward to credit and believe them.</hi> Which Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony being of one of their own Party, is a clear Evidence againſt this Bloody Church, that the only Crime of theſe Perſons, was their ſo freely declaring againſt the Idolatry and Corruptions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; and therefore that the inhumane Butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of them was a groſs and heynous Murder in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſaore comes next to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of which <hi>Thuanus</hi> ſays, <hi>Nullum ſimilis ſaevitae exemplum in tota Antiquitate reperiri;</hi> i. e. the moſt Ancient Records cannot furniſh us with an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the like cruelty; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt l.</hi> 52, 53.</note> it was cloaked over with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62067:40"/>ſhews of the greateſt Amity in the World, namely, of a Marriage between the Houſes of <hi>Valois</hi> and <hi>Bourbon,</hi> to which all the chief of the Proteſtants were moſt lovingly invited: There, after the jollity of Mirth, and Careſſes of Entertainment, in the dead time of the Night, the whole City was in Arms about them; they fell upon all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, Houſes and Lodgings; they butcher'd them without diſtinction, Men, Women, and Children, till the Channels ran down with blood into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: thirty thouſand perſons were there murdered, ſays <hi>Thuanus,</hi> and as many more about that time in divers places of
<hi>France,</hi> ſays <hi>Natales Comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Cruelty was celebrated by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt.</hi> l. <hi>25.</hi> Circiter Sexaginta millia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum variis in locis per il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus truci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data fuiſſe dicta ſunt in Gallia.</note> as one of the moſt glorious Actions the World hath been acquainted with; great rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings at Court for it, and Publick Thanks given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: But the greateſt joy was at <hi>Rome,</hi> an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of which take from <hi>Thuanus,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and a moſt Authemick Hiſtorian: He tells us the Pope had an account of the Maſſacre from his Legate at <hi>Paris,</hi> that he read his Letter in the Conſiſtoby of Cardinals, that there it was decreed, that they ſhould go directly to S. <hi>Mark</hi>'s, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 53.</note> and there ſolemnly give Thanks to Almighty God for ſo great a Bleſſing conferred upon the <hi>Roman</hi> See, and the Chriſtian World: That ſoon after a <hi>Jubilee</hi> ſhould be publiſh through the whole Chriſtian World, and theſe Cauſes were expreſt for it, <hi>To give thanks to God for deſtroying in</hi> France <hi>the Enemies of the Truth, and of the Church.</hi> In the Evening the Guns were fired at S. <hi>Angeto,</hi> and Bonefires were made,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62067:40"/>and nothing was omitted of all thoſe things that uſe to be performed in the greateſt Victories of the Church. Some days after there was a Proceſſion to S.
<hi>Lewis,</hi> with the greateſt reſort of Nobility and People: Firſt went the Biſhops and Cardinals, then the <hi>Switzers,</hi> then the Ambaſſadors of Kings and Princes; then under a Canopy went his Holineſs himſell, with the Emperour's Ambaſſador bearing up his Train for him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Over the Church-door was an Inſcription ſet up, in which the Cardinal of
<hi>Lorrain,</hi> in the name of the King of <hi>France,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulated his Holineſs, and the College of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the plainly ſtupendious effects, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together incredible events of their Counſels given him, and of their Aſſiſtances ſent him, and of their twelve years Wiſhes and Prayers. And the better to perpetuate the memory of this Maſſacre, the Pope cauſed it to be painted about his great Hall in the <hi>Lateran,</hi> and there recorded in Marble.</p>
            <p>To theſe bloody Catalogues a conſiderable Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion has been made ſince by the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland;</hi> who in times of as great peace and liberty as ever that Nation enjoyed; and in the name of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and gracious King, <note place="margin">The Lord
<hi>Orory</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Welſh, p.</hi> 29. ſaith, within few Months about two hundred thouſand.</note> under whom they enjoyed theſe, like inhumane Butchers, cut the throats of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a hundred thouſand of his Proteſtant Subjects, of all Sexes and Ages; an action of ſo horrid an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, as will make the names of all that had to do in it look black and deteſtable to mankind through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Generations:
<q>That Sea of Blood which hath there been cruelly and barbarouſly ſhed, is enough to drown any man in Eternal, both infamy and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, whom God ſhall find the malicious Author, or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62067:41"/>Inſtigator of its Effuſion, <hi>Icon Baſil. c.</hi> 12.</q> And how far his Holineſs was concerned in it, appears by his <hi>Nuncio</hi> whom he ſent to promote and bleſs the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed what I intended to ſay in this ſhort Diſcourſe, with no other deſign, than that of doing Honour to God, and vindicating the abuſed Glory of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, by ſhewing how far the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is degenerated from his Goſpel, who is indeed the Prince and Head of the Catholick Church; whom I humbly beſeech to open the Eyes of all deluded Perſons, that they may come to the knowledge of the Truth, and be ſaved. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62067:41"/>
            <head>Book's Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhops-Head in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s
<hi>Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>H. <hi>Mori Opera Theologica,</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>—His Reply to a late Anſwer to his Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Idolatry, with an Appendix, in
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Remarks in anſwer to the Lord <hi>Hales</hi> of Gravitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Non-gravitation of Fluids, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Falkner</hi>'s <hi>Libertas Ecoleſiaſtica,</hi> in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Chriſtian Loyalty, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and our Union and Communion with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which is annexed a Defence, and Continuation; with a particular reſpect to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Charge of
<hi>Socinianiſm</hi> and <hi>Relagianiſm,</hi> in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hotchkis</hi>'s Diſcourſe concerning the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to us, and our Sins to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in two Parts, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Ferguſſon,</hi> about Juſtification, in
<hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Myſtery of Iniquity unfolded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Chriſtians Juſtification ſtated, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Friendly Advice to the Non-Conformiſts, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Anabaptiſts, in
<hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hallywel</hi>'s Account of Familiſm againſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Diſcourſe of the Excellency of Chriſtianity, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Sacred Method of ſaving Humane Souls by Jeſus Chriſt, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Goodall</hi>'s Vindication of the College of Phyſitians, againſt a Pamphlet called, The Corner-ſtone, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Grew</hi>'s Anatomy of Trunks, with 19 Figures, in <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
